<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the death of the most illustrious lord, Sigr. Troilo Sauelli, a Baron of Rome who was there beheaded, in the castle of Sant-Angelo, on the 18. of April, 1592. With a preface, conteyning diuers particulers, which are wholy necessary to be knowne, for the better vnderstanding of the relation it selfe.</title>
            <author>Biondi, Giuseppe, 1537-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838476</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2857</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2857)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 654:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the death of the most illustrious lord, Sigr. Troilo Sauelli, a Baron of Rome who was there beheaded, in the castle of Sant-Angelo, on the 18. of April, 1592. With a preface, conteyning diuers particulers, which are wholy necessary to be knowne, for the better vnderstanding of the relation it selfe.</title>
                  <author>Biondi, Giuseppe, 1537-1598.</author>
                  <author>Matthew, Tobie, Sir, 1577-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 255, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Giuseppe Biondi.</note>
                  <note>Italian original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Translated by Sir Tobie Matthew.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures A²  ² A-Q.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A relation of the death of signor Troilo Sauelli.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 51-62 (D2-D7) lacking in original item.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Savelli, Troilo, d. 1592 --  Death and burial --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2857:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2857:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE DEATH, OF THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS LORD, Sig.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Troilo Sauelli, <hi>a Baron of Rome;</hi> Who was there beheaded, in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Sant-Angelo, on the 18. of Aprill, 1592.</p>
            <p>With a Preface, conteyning diuers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, which are wholy neceſſary to be knowne, for the better vnderſtanding of the Relation it ſelfe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Domine, quis ſimilis tibi?</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Pſal. 34.</bibl>
               <p>O Lord, who is like to thee?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum, M.DC.XX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2857:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2857:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> following, hath beene tranſlated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diuers lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages; though not at all into ours, nor yet ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2857:3"/>into others, out of the true Original <hi>Italian,</hi> as I could haue wished. The differences between the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, which walke vp, and downe the world, are not great; ſauing, that when there is queſtion of truth; and that, concerning a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubiect; and the ſame, accompanyed with variety of naturall, and liuely cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, I cannot find in my hart, to let any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence goe for ſmall. I haue therefore, at once, taken both paynes, and pleaſure, <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2857:3"/>to draw ſtore of copyes into my hand, and it hath not beene without ſucceſſe. For if I haue not layd hold vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very firſt <hi>Original,</hi> which was written by the Relatour himſelfe; I dare ſay, that I am growne very neere it, &amp; that it is preciſely true. And this <hi>Elogium</hi> I will be bold to giue to the Diſcourſe, which we haue in hand, that it hath beene reade in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral countryes with extreme auidity. Nay perhaps there hath not iſſued, in many of theſe laſt ages, any one hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2857:4"/>
               <hi>Relation,</hi> of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer accident, the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">The relation follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath been ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome read without tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof, hath more often beene attended by teares, then this.</p>
            <p>The
<note n="(b)" place="margin">The birth, &amp; perſon, &amp; parts of this Noble Man.</note> Perſon whome it concerneth, was a <hi>Baron</hi> of
<hi>Rome, Sig.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Troilo Sauelli;</hi> a braunch, which ſprunge vp, from a root of as noble bloud, as a moſt certaine extractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the ancient
<hi>Romans,</hi> could tell how to make it. His perſon, &amp; the parts of his generous mind, are beſt deſcribed in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> it ſelfe, which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2857:4"/>ſo that, I will not heere by putting you to paynes, preuent the pleaſure which there you wil haue to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them. The cauſe for which he ſuffered, is not ſpecified there at all; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his ghoſtly Father was the penner of this narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and it became not him, who was the others Iudge <hi>in foro Conſcientiae,</hi> to become his Accuſer, <hi>in foro Curiae.</hi> For although his crimes were extant then, and are ſo ſtil vpon <hi>Record;</hi> and that the penitent did beſids (for <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2857:5"/>his owne greater confuſion, and the exaltation of the inuincible Patience, and Mercy of Almighty God) giue his Ghoſtly Father ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe leaue, to declare his ſinnes to the whole world; the Father yet, would by no meanes accept of that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but ſpeaking only in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall wordes, of ſinne at large; he
<note n="(c)" place="margin">The inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeale of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; &amp; how ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a good Ghoſtly Father, is, and ought to be.</note> burieth the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulers in profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſilence, and vnder the ſeale of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion,</hi> for reuerence of that holy
<hi>Sacrament,</hi> which muſt neuer vpon any termes be defaced.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2857:5"/>
            <p>But I, who am free, will not conſent to haue my handes tyed vp; but doe think it fit to let you know, that although his yeares were few, his crimes were great, &amp; many; as doth ſtil appeare vpon the <hi>Record</hi> of his <hi>Proceſſe.</hi> And betweene the ſixteenth, and the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth yeare of his age (till the former of which tymes, his vigilant, and holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was able to keep him in the diſcipline of piety, &amp; vertue) he ſprouted out, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to great exorbitances; and <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2857:6"/>in the Company, and at the head of the
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Theſe are men who for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; other extreme inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes vſe to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. They were wont in Italy, to go, in great troopes vp and downe, &amp; to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the paſſages. <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> was one of the firſt, who broke their backe.</note> 
               <hi>Banditi,</hi> he committed both rapes and murthers, with a moſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous, and tranſported mind. <hi>Ominis
<note n="(e)" place="margin">The bane which is brought vpon young noble men by ill company.</note> inimica amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ſeductio me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis inueſtigabilis.</hi> He did too early, caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into the hands of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, &amp; wicked followers; and they made the way of ſinne ſo ſmooth to him, as that he could not hold fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſliding through it. Nor was his tender youth ſo inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2857:6"/>nor his education ſo excellent, but that the moath, and canker of lewd company, did ſoon corrode it.</p>
            <p>Yet euen heerein, was not his miſery ſo great, as the
<note n="(f)" place="margin">It is proper to God alone, to draw good out of euill.</note> mercy of God, vpon this occaſion, was infinite. His crims were not known, but by ſuch alone, as would not eaſily aduenture to draw vpon themſelues, the diſpleaſure of ſo greate a houſe as his, by detecting them. The manner only of his life, in reſpect of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2857:7"/>and riot, was ſuch, in the exteriour, as wounded his noble, and tender Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the very ſoule. The paſſages, and proceedinges whereof, are deliuered in the <hi>Relation</hi> it ſelfe, with ſo greate tendernes, in the perſon of her ſonne, as ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes the hart of him that reades the wordes. I will not therfore touch that flowre, for feare of ſtrikng off the dew, euery dropp whereof is a pearle. One circumſtance only which is not mentioned there, I will <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2857:7"/>heer expreſſe; becauſe it wil not faile to ſerue, towardes the increaſe of compaſſion, in all their mindes, who reade this ſtory.</p>
            <p>You
<note n="(g)" place="margin">A cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, towards the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> shall therfore vnderſtand, that when the Mother had vſed all other poſſible endeauours, both diuine and humane, for the reduction, and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her ſonne, and all in vaine (for ought that she was able to perceiue) she cauſed him, for ſome offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (which yet, were farre from being Capitall) to be <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2857:8"/>committed to Caſtle (k) <hi>S. Angelo;</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">This is the chiefe priſon in Rome, as the Tower may be in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> in hope that ſuch a diſgrace, with the help of tyme, would make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into hmſelf. To this courſe she was the more encouraged, &amp; in this hope the more confirmed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by this reſtraint, he would be cut off from that ill company, which was the very peſt, and poiſon of his ſoule. But ſee, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at Gods prouidence. He
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Any little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique diſgrace carryeth danger with it,</note> was no ſooner in priſon, but the fire of eager oppoſition brake forth of <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2857:8"/>their hartes, whom, by his other more enormous inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencyes, he had offended; for till then, it had beene ſmoothered vnder the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes of that reſpect, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, which they carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards the Dignity, &amp; Nobility of his houſe. But now <hi>publique Iuſtice</hi> taking notice of his exceſſes; and <hi>Pope Clement</hi> the eight, in the beginning of his
<hi>Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,</hi> being deſirous to shew a ſtrong example, of what vnpartiall <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> the world was to expect at his hands;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2857:9"/>(eſpecially in repreſſing, &amp; extinguishing that afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid damned crue of <hi>Banditi,</hi> who were ſo pernicious to the State of <hi>Italy,</hi> and of whom this yong Lord was growne a leader) did ſuffer the law to paſſe vpon his perſon (for his ſtate was not confiſcated, but went to his heyres, in bloud). Being euen yet therin, more
<hi>Iuſt,</hi> then <hi>Clement;</hi> though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he would haue been more
<hi>Clement</hi> in pardoning, then <hi>Iuſt</hi> in punishing; if he could, by way of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation, <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2857:9"/>haue ſeene the beauty, and brauery of that noble ſpirit, which deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to liue as longe, as a world can do; as a patterne, of a mind moſt rarely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, between perfect Chriſtian piety, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted incomparable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimity.</p>
            <p>But whyleſt the
<note n="(k)" place="margin">This Lady dyed in the year 1611. and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on the 21. of October in the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines Church at <hi>Sant Andrea della val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le;</hi> wher ſhe ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ten maſſes to be ſayd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day, for euer. She was of the houſe of the Dukes of <hi>Ceſi;</hi> and ſiſter to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Riano;</hi> her name was <hi>la Signo a Flaminia.</hi>
               </note> Mother, and the Sonne, are both of them reſtinge now in peace, and glory, as we may piouſly belieue; I know <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2857:10"/>not how, in this particuler, to be ſilent, concerning the powerfull, and wiſe, and infinitely good
<note n="(l)" place="margin">The proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth to be deeply ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler.</note> proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, of Almighty God, towardes both theſe ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of his. For, by the way of the
<note n="(m)" place="margin">The Croſſe is the high way to heauen.</note> 
               <hi>Croſſe,</hi> he brought the ſonne, in a few momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of time, to haue a ſoule in ſtate of great perfection; and he gaue him, in the laſt houres of his life, that moſt happy kind of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> wherin he might not only ſuffer, in ſatiſfaction of the diuine
<hi>Iustice,</hi> but paſſe <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2857:10"/>on by <hi>merittes,</hi> (all groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the mercy of <hi>Ieſus</hi> Chriſt our
<note n="(n)" place="margin">No action of man is merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, but by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and firſt mercy of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</note> Lord (as all merits are) towards inſtant, and eternall felicity.</p>
            <p>And this he did, by as contrary meanes, as in the
<hi>Ghoſpell</hi> he cured a certaine <hi>Blind man,</hi> by
<note n="(o)" place="margin">The omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of God, is not tyed to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but workes his will, how he will.</note> 
               <hi>caſting durt vpon his eyes.</hi> For heer be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the moſt indulgent ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der care of the mother, who loued that Sonne, as her owne ſoule; towardes the bringing that about, which was indeed, to make him happy in the end; but in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2857:11"/>meane tyme, was the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his ſuddaine, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull death, whereby her very hart was to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Taking him ſo from her ſight, that ſo she might enioy a glorious ſight of him for euer; &amp; depriuing her of all humane comforts (which (for as much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned her) were abridged, &amp; locked vp in him alone) that ſo she might, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world, ſend her whole hart vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whither now her trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was gone before; and ſo <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2857:11"/>be rewarded, for that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and entire care, which she had taken, for his pious education.</p>
            <p>It
<note n="(p)" place="margin">The blind &amp; blocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of worldly men.</note> matters not much, what the blind, and dull world conceaues; which placing fayth in fancy; and religious reaſon in the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous ſenſe of flesh and bloud; thinkes all that to be miſery, which carryeth the face of paine, or shame, or any difficulty; and that true happines conſiſtes in rowing for a whyle in ſome boate
<note n="(q)" place="margin">A fit emblem to ſhew the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of worldly pleaſure.</note> of muſike, downe <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2857:12"/>the tide; though it carry them ſoone after, where they are either to be ſplit vpon rockes, or ſwallowed vp by quick-ſandes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God knowes (yea &amp; men whohaue his grace, are not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r therof) that a courſe of felicity, not interrupted, or checked by contrary windes, is a kind of fortune (for as much as concerneth the next life) which in this, deſerueth rather pitty, then enuy; and that, euer fince the death of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, the way of the <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2857:12"/>
               <hi>Croſſe,</hi> is
<note n="(r)" place="margin">The croſſe of Chriſt our Lord, hath made miſery, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come happy.</note> not only the more ſafe, but euen the more honorable; and that the pleaſures, and paſtimes of this life, ar but a kind of butterfly, for boyes to play withall; &amp; that the greateſt earthly felicity, that euer was enioyed by man, if it dyed not as ſoone as it was borne (which yet is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary caſe of
<note n="(s)" place="margin">World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſpeakes faire, but it lyes.</note> worldly ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſure) at leaſt, if it liued til it could learne to ſpeake, it told as many lies, as it vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wordes; and charmed them firſt, whom quickly <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2857:13"/>after, it might lead towards a precipice.</p>
            <p>How deſolate, would a worldling thinke, that the caſe of
<hi>Signor Troylo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelli</hi> was, in that night when he receaued the newes of his ſo inſtantely approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelious death? And of that deare Mother of his, when she heard the blow was giuen, which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that head from thoſe shoulders? And
<note n="(t)" place="margin">Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, made the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; the Son, ſeeme miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</note> yet with all, is it both well knowne, that the Mothers loſſe of ſuch a ſonne, did caſt her
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2857:13"/>much more cloſe, vpon an vnion and ſole dependance for all her comfort, vpon Almighty God; (wherein the happines, which we can haue in this life conſiſts) and it is morally certaine, that the abundant grace of Contrition, and Charity, which God infuſed into the hart of the
<hi>Sonne,</hi> euen by the occaſion of his very ſins (ſo vaſtly &amp; infinitely good is God) did put him inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, after his death, into a ſtate ſo bleſſed, as that the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe, vnder whom
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2857:14"/>he died, and thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> amongſt whom he liued, and all the <hi>Monarches</hi> of the whole world, may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to haue bin miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, according to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, in reſpect of him. Our deare Lord <hi>Ieſus,</hi> be eternally thanked (&amp; not only by vs, who know not how to do it well, but by all his holy Angells, and Sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes) for his owne infinite goodnes; ſince he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes to
<note n="(u)" place="margin">He could eaſily honour himſelfe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, without any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to vs, if he were ſo pleaſed.</note> place the point of his Honour, in shewing mercyes, and working won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2857:14"/>vpon man, ſo inſtantly, ſo ſweetely, ſo powerfully, and ſo like a God. And for hauing ſuffered, in his owne ſacred ſoule, &amp; body, ſuch deſolations, and torments, as obtained, at the handes of the eternall Father, not only the remiſſion of our ſinnes, (if we will ſerue our ſelues of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and other remedyes which he hath left in the boſome of his holy <hi>Catholike Church</hi>) but the adorninge alſo of our ſoules, with the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent giftes, and graces of <pb n="26" facs="tcp:2857:15"/>the holy Ghoſt. And yet further, for that he hath knowne, how to make our very ſinnes, and greiuous crimes themſelues, the meanes, ſome times, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we obtaine greater gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then
<note n="(x)" place="margin">This indeed is a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which may wel become the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atnes of our God.</note> we should haue done, if we had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thoſe very ſinnes. Let the whole world ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adore thee, O Lord, and ſing prayſes to thee; and let all the powers of all ſoules cry out, and ſay with that holy King, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid, O Lord who is like to thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2857:15"/>
            <p>A great example, and proofe of this power of God, and of the diuinity of Chriſt our Lord, and the vnſpeakable bounty of the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> was the ſo ſpeedy illuminating, &amp; inflaming the ſoule of this <hi>Baron.</hi> Who, as ſoone as he recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the notice of his death, did, in his proportion, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the example of the <hi>Bleſſed Apoſtle.</hi> For as he, to Chriſt our Lord, appearing ſayd, <hi>O Lord, what wilt thou haue me doe;</hi> ſo did this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Caualliere of Chriſt,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2857:16"/>when the Preiſt, &amp; Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God ſpake to him, giue himſelfe away by theſe words, as the <hi>Relation</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;
<hi>Do
<note n="(y)" place="margin">The inſtant quiet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this Baron to the good wil of God.</note> you, in the place of God commaund me, I giue my ſelfe, as bound into your hands;</hi> and further it affirmeth, that he ſuffered himſelfe to be managed, as if he had beene made, of the ſofteſt waxe.</p>
            <p>It is not impoſſible for a man to meete with ſome Roaring Boy, who may thinke that the <hi>Baron</hi> was to ſubmiſſe. But it is one <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2857:16"/>thing to be a Roarer of the damned Crue, and another to be an humble member of the body of Chriſt; who aſſured vs, by his owne ſacred mouth, <hi>That
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is the true badge, of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we became as children, we should neuer enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</hi> The world was loſt by the
<hi>pride,</hi> and preſumption of the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> &amp; repaired by the <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the ſecond. And
<note n="(a)" place="margin">The incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</note> he that conſiders well, how greate that
<hi>Humility</hi> was; and whoſe it was; and for whoſe ſake, and at the will <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2857:17"/>of whom, he exerciſed the fame; had need of a great proportion of ſtupidity, to make him thinke, that, ſince God himſelfe vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to be at the command of thoſe baſe and impure wretches, who tooke of his cloathes, and required him to ſubmit himſelfe to thoſe ſcourges, thoſe thornes, thoſe nayles, thoſe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for our ſakes, and ſinnes; yet, on the other ſide, this
<note n="(b)" place="margin">An vgly and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> man, this proud rebellious worme, this crumme of duſt, this drop <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2857:17"/>of filth; might keep, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, a kind of State, and should not rather ſubmit himſelfe (in imitation of the humility of Chriſt our Lord) not only to Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, but to equalls, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen inferiours alſo, and in fine to al
<note n="(c)" place="margin">This is the aduice of <hi>S.</hi> Peter;
<hi>Subdits eſtote omni creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae.</hi>
               </note> the world when iuſt occaſion should be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</p>
            <p>The ſoule of this noble Man, was ſo well ſoftned, &amp; ſweetned, by the vnction of the Holy Ghoſt; as that neither the greatnes of his Nobility, nor the ardour of <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2857:18"/>his youth, nor the naturall boyling courage of his hart, nor the fresh memory of his proſperity, nor the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected arriual of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fery, could make
<note n="(d)" place="margin">A hart which is truely touched by Gods holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtrange difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes.</note> him once repine, or keep him from inſtantly abaſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. But falling deeply v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſinnes; and weighing duely how full of demerit he was, in the ſight of God; and knowing exactly, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo truly ignoble, as a ſoule which hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited his grace; and that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2857:18"/>
               <hi>rich,</hi> or <hi>poore,</hi> is little to the purpoſe; but
<note n="(c)" place="margin">wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, true Nobility doth conſiſt.</note> that the thing which imports, is to be, or not to be, the ſeruant, or ſonne of God; it is not ſtrange, to ſee him caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at the feet of common ſoldiars; and to ſtretch out his hands, with ſuch meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, at the will of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt laylours, for the loue of our Lord, to ſignify ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the deteſtation wherein he had himſelfe, for hauing ſo preſumptuouſly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that <hi>Eternall Maieſty,</hi> which by all the Angells is <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2857:19"/>adored.</p>
            <p>From
<note n="(f)" place="margin">The reaſons why he was ſo frequent in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing his ſins.</note> hence alſo did it proceed, that he ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently confeſſed himſelfe, in that laſt night of his life; &amp; could neuer thinke that he had ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly deplored his errours, and deteſted the diſcorreſpondence, and ingratitude, wherewith he had anſwered, the vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able benefits, of Almighty God. Wherein if any man should thinke, that he did vſe exceſſe; it willbe much more lawfull for me to doubt, that himſelfe, either <pb n="35" facs="tcp:2857:19"/>hath a meane conceit of the <hi>Infinite Maieſty</hi> which is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; or an ignorant ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, of the deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of al ſinne which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; or a proud, &amp; pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try miſtaking, of the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> which man was, till he was created; and the worſe then <hi>Nothing,</hi> which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he grew, by ſinning. For
<note n="(g)" place="margin">If you weigh theſe thinges wel, you will change your won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring at him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring at your ſelfe.</note> he that po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders theſe particulers, as he ought; and knoweth, that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces into which he falleth are innumerable; and that the leaſt of them, which is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2857:20"/>committed againſt an <hi>infinit Maieſty,</hi> in reſpect of the obiect, is alſo infinite; and that, as no one good deed shalbe vnrewarded, by the rich Mercy of God, in Chriſt our Lord; ſo no one tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſion shal be left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished, by his exquiſite Iuſtice; will eaſily belieue, that in the ſpace of a night, it is hard for one to be too curious, &amp; too carefull, in ſetting ſtraight the accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his whole life, vnder the piercing eye of Almighty God. But this <hi>Baron,</hi> did, <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2857:20"/>euen by moments, in that short tyme which was left, by the goodnes of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire new
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Great light of God is wont to breed greate loue of him, &amp; greate ſorrow, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him.</note> light, &amp; gaine new loue of our Lord, and new contempt, &amp; deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of himſelfe; and in the ſtrength thereof, he found ſome actions to confeſſe, which he had not concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be ſinnes before; &amp; others which he had confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he had confeſſed with a ſorrow, far inferiour, to that which then he felt.</p>
            <p>For abſtracting from the conſideration which he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2857:21"/>had of his ſinnes, againſt God (in reſpecte whereof, no ſoule is ſufficiently able to quake, and tremble vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him) I truſt there is not a readers eye in the world ſo dimme, as not to diſcerne his vndaunted hart. And
<note n="(i)" place="margin">The vndaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of this Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</note> that, no thought of death, had any power, to take the leaſt clarity from his vnderſtandinge; the leaſt preſence from his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; the leaſt agility from his witte; the leaſt order from his ſpeach; or ſo much as the leaſt <hi>puntillio,</hi> from <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2857:21"/>the ciuill reſpects and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementes, which are vſed amongſt perſons of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Condition. Nor yet, on the other ſide, shall any man haue reaſon to thinke, that the punctuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which (throughout the proceſſe of this <hi>Relation</hi>) he shall find to haue been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by the
<hi>Baron,</hi> in this laſt
<note n="(k)" place="margin">This courteſy &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement was not affected, but free and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall.</note> kind of courteſy, did proceed from the leaſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation thereof. Perhaps, if we looke neere home, we may find ſome example to haue been giuen of this, not <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2857:22"/>longe agoe; but in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent caſe, no ſuſpition of it, can be intertained; both for many other reaſons, which will occurre to him that readeth the
<hi>Relation;</hi> and becauſe (as I ſayd before) theſe exact tearmes of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and other reſpects to the company, which then is preſent, are is it were natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to men of his country, and quality; and there would coſt them more pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to omit them (vnleſſe their mindes were put into diſorder, by ſome paſſion) <pb n="41" facs="tcp:2857:22"/>then it would coſt others, to obſerue them, where they were not ſo naturall, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing learnt by induſtry, and art. But yet, that in ſo ſad a caſe, this man, would, for good manners, forbeare to ſet vp his leggs; or would not ſo much, as ſtretch him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ſight of others, though his body did much incline him to it (according to that mention which the <hi>Relation</hi> makes therof) may wel go for a great argument in him, of ciuility, of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and of magnanimity.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:2857:23"/>
            <p>And this is that which I thought fit to repreſent to you, by way of <hi>Preface,</hi> to this <hi>Story.</hi> You will find the traces &amp; foot-ſteps of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting men to death, and of the proceedinge which is held with
<note n="(l)" place="margin">The ſeuerall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners, of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes.</note> delinquents, to be very different, from that of our Countrey, both concerning the body, and the ſoule. I take not vpon me, to ſay which are better, and which are worſe. With vs, the <hi>Proceſſe</hi> of criminall perſons, is euer made, in the face of the world; but they <pb n="43" facs="tcp:2857:23"/>are not ſuffered to haue any aduocates who may defend their cauſes. In moſt other Countryes, the delinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are permitted to haue Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocates, but the <hi>Proceſſe</hi> is made, though in publique Court, yet only in preſence of the Iudges and ſome few Aduocates, and Officers. With vs, the delinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are ſuffered to liue ſome dayes after their comdemnation; which certainely is meant in compaſſion to them; in other parts, after they are iudged to dye, and that ſo it <pb n="44" facs="tcp:2857:24"/>is declared, they thinke they do men a greater cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy, in putting them quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of paine. With vs, there is no difference in the manner of death, between a Clowne, &amp; the beſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Kingdome, vnder the degree of a <hi>Baron,</hi> vnleſſe it be, in ſome very rare caſe, by moſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler fauour of his
<hi>Maieſty;</hi> but in all other places, that I haue ſeene, all Gentlemen are beheaded, to diſtinguish them, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. With vs, no indignity <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2857:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>is euer done to a <hi>Noble man</hi> of
<note n="(m)" place="margin">ſuch as Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are, and al aboue them.</note> 
               <hi>Title,</hi> by binding of his hands, or armes, or the like; and that cuſtome I commend, as full of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; but in many other places, they beare no ſuch reſpects; in regard of the experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which they haue found, and I feare, which ſtill they are in, of inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>But for as much, as concernes the comfort of criminalls, in the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ſoules, towards the death of their bodyes,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2857:25"/>I cannot but note it, as a point of charity, and piety moſt
<note n="(n)" place="margin">It is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to help me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dye well.</note> remarkeable, that in very many of the good townes of
<hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spayne,</hi> there are certain <hi>Companies,</hi> or
<hi>Confraternities,</hi> of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, well borne and bred; who put this obligation of duty vpon themſelues, to viſit the priſons, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the night prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to any executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And, togeather with Religious perſons, and Ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they watch, and pray, and exhort, and comfort <pb n="47" facs="tcp:2857:25"/>the pooreſt criminalls of the Country, with the ſame induſtry, &amp; charity, which is heere, affoarded to this Noble man. And they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them all, to their death; and ſometimes, they diſcharge their dying harts of care; either by vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking to pay ſome of their debtes, or by aſſiſting the poore wife, and children, which are left behind; or by obliging themſelues, to get
<note n="(o)" place="margin">S. Monies vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the point of her death, deſired S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine her Sonne, that he would pray for her ſoule at the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſhould be dead: and ſo he did. <hi>Vide Auguſt. Confeſ. l.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Maſſes</hi> celebrated for their ſoules. And in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of theſe good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, <pb n="48" facs="tcp:2857:26"/>we ſee men dye in thoſe partes, with another manner of diſpoſition to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes God, then vſually they haue with vs. Where it is a lamentable thing, to ſee many of ſo profane ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity, that after liues moſt lewdly lead, they go either drunke, or dauncing to the gallowes. As if, they were but to dye in a play; or as if, after this life, there were no immortality of the ſoule; or els, at leaſt, no account to be rendred, I ſay not, of idle words (which yet muſt <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2857:26"/>be done) but of moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deeds, wherof many of them are guilty.</p>
            <p>The example which heere we haue in hand, will read, to all the Readers of it in generall, a good leſſon of humility, patience, cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy, magnanimity, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and charity. And
<note n="(p)" place="margin">All kind of people may profit, by the good leſſons which are heer deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> it may ſerue for an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, not only to ſuch as dye, by the hand of human Iuſtice; but to al them alſo, who are to dye by the hand of God, as we al shalbe ſure inough to do. That ſo, we <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2857:27"/>may the better take heede of ſinne, which is to be ſo bitterly bewayled; and the more deeply we be fallen into it, the more inſtantly we muſt implore the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp; goodnes of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God; and diſpoſe our ſelues to the doing of pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; that ſo, by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, we may ſecure our ſoules, from the danger of being plunged, into that lake of eternall paine. This leſſon I ſay, may reach to al Readers in generall. But particuler Readers may
<gap reason="missing" extent="12 pages">
                  <desc>〈12 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:2857:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>friend,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">The earely, &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this Noble man.</note> ſayth he, <hi>behould, I am heere, ready to obey thy will, and the will of all the world, ſince the will of God is ſuch.</hi> Hauing manicled him, they
<note n="(g)" place="margin">By this time others were come in.</note> lead him towardes the Chappell; when, at the iſſue out of his chamber, he bleſſed
<note n="(h)" place="margin">He armed himſelfe with the ſigne of the holy Croſſe <hi>Ad om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, ad omnem ntceſſum manus ping at Crucem:</hi> At euery action, and in euery motion let thy hand make the ſigne of the Croſſe, <hi>D. Hier. epiſt. ad Euſtoch,</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi>
16.</note> himſelf, the beſt he could with the ſigne of the holy
<hi>Croſſe,</hi> with both his hands; and caſting vp his eyes to heauen, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly ſighed. For, ſeeing perhappes, that there was
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2857:28"/>more people, then might beneedful for the changing of his lodging, <hi>This,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>is another manner of buſines, then to change me only, from one place to another; but by the grace of God, I am ready for all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, filently going downe to the Chappell, he was mett by the
<note n="(i)" place="margin">There are <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen in Rome (as there are alſo in other great Cittyes of Italy &amp; Spay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) who imploy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for the helping of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned men, to dye, wol. The <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour</hi> and <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueditore</hi> are chiefe officers of theſe Congregations.</note> 
               <hi>Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> &amp; the
<hi>Proueditore,</hi> and by three others of them, who are called
<hi>Confortatori della miſericordia,</hi> in a fashio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, very ſutable to the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Then one of them ſayd <pb n="65" facs="tcp:2857:28"/> to him in this manner:
<q rend="margQuotes">My Lord, the houre which God hath prefixed for you, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen run out; render your ſelfe into his mercifull han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</q> And he, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing troubled, otherwiſe, then by fetching a ſighe (which yet was both ſoft, &amp; short) did anſwere thus; <hi>Let God be bleſſed; behold I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my ſelfe to him; and diſpoſe you of me</hi> And ſo thoſe good and charitable Brothers of that
<hi>Congregation,</hi> with ſome Fathers of the <hi>Society of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> caſting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues round <pb n="66" facs="tcp:2857:29"/>about him; and endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſweeten the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of that newes, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet &amp; decent meanes, did comfort him the beſt they could. He yielded to all, &amp; did euen preuent them; &amp; then, knocking his breſt, and bowing down his head, and kiſſing the <hi>Crucifixe,</hi> he demanded pardon, and like gentle waxe, did ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be managed by them all.</p>
            <p>One of thoſe <hi>Conforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori,</hi> did, before all other thinges, put him in mind <pb n="67" facs="tcp:2857:29"/>of making his
<hi>Confeſſion.</hi> V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the very firſt naming whereof (recollecting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) he ſayd, <hi>And
<note n="(k)" place="margin">The firſt thing he did, was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe himſelf.</note> where is the Confeſſour?</hi> And they shewing him a Prieſt of their Company, with his <hi>Albe</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Theſe are ſome of the ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes which are vſed in the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Maſſe.</note> vpon his backe, and his <hi>Stole</hi> about his necke (that afterward he might ſay Maſſe, in the proper tyme) the firſt thing he did, was to be confeſſed; and we all went out, to leaue the place free to them.</p>
            <p>He being confeſſed, and we returned, we began to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2857:30"/>diſpoſe him, towards a good end, by diuers ſpiritual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, fit for that purpoſe. And after many had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I alſo beganne thus to ſay;
<q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> This is that paſſage, which whoſoeuer doth once make well, doth acquire eternall felicity; &amp; if once it be ill made, it draweth after it, an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting miſery. It now imports your Lordship to make it well, that you may eſcape that eternity of torment. This paſſage is narrow, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euen, hard, &amp; full of ſtones, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:2857:30"/>and thornes; all the world doth ſee it, and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship finds it by experience;</q> but
<note n="(m)" place="margin">Our Lord Ieſus, doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the vneuen way of death.</note> behold ſweet Ieſus, who, by his goodnes, will euen it all. Caſt your ſelfe, my Lord, vpon him; and then you will be able to ſay with courage, <hi>Omnia
<note n="(n)" place="margin">I can do al thinges in him that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts me.</note> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, in eo qui me confortat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He anſwered thus, with a cheerefull, and euen ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance, <hi>Omnia poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum in eo qui me comfortat. By the mercy of my deere Ieſus, I know the neceſſity of making this paſſage well; I acknowledge his <pb n="70" facs="tcp:2857:31"/>prouidence ouer me, and to his prouidence I add, that, of his ioue. Ror as much as with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary loue it is, that he hath brought me hither. I ſee it, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it. And how often, deere Father, haue I beene, as I may ſay, in the very iawes of death; which if at that tyme it had ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed vpon me, infallibly this ſoule, and body of myne had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished. Behold
<note n="(o)" place="margin">He acknow ledgeth, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, with great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacrity.</note> the cunning of my Christ; to ſaue me, he hath made choyce of this way.</hi> And then bowing, &amp; baring his head, and with great life of ſpirit, rayſing himſelf from
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2857:31"/>his chayre, he further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; <hi>I accept of this election, which God hath made;</hi> &amp; then caſting himſelfe vpon his knees, before the <hi>Altar, Nay I thanke thee</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>O my good Father, for thy ſo fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and louing care of me; who haue not only beene a wandring, but a contumacious Sonne of thyne. To thee it doth belong, to ſmooth and euen the rugged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this way; ſince thou haſt been pleaſed to addreſſe me by it.</hi> And ſo, bowing his face euen almoſt downe to the ground, he remayned a <pb n="72" facs="tcp:2857:32"/>while, in men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all Prayer.</p>
            <p>Being therfore wished to ſit downe, he was ſcarce ſetled in that poſture, when turning towardes me, he ſayd thus, in myne eare:
<hi>You, whom through my good fortune, I haue heere, to help me, in this ſo weighty and high affayre, in the place of God do yow commaund me. I
<note n="(p)" place="margin">He giueth himſelfe away to his Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> giue my ſelfe, as bound into your hands. The Prince hath diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my body; do you as much with my ſoule.</hi> I ſayd therfore to him: I firſt deſyre, my Lord, that you make the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2857:32"/>
               <hi>proteſtation</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">This is a decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration of his fayth with an entiere ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the good will of God.</note> which is wont to be beliuered by ſuch as are going to God. Which being publikely pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by him, with great ſenſe and ſpirit, (he taking vp &amp; repeating my wordes) I aduiſed him further thus:
<q rend="margQuotes">Yow shall now make all thoſe actes of Contrition, which I shall call to your mind; hauing the eyes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, firſt bent vpon God, being offended, as a <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,</hi> as a
<hi>Preſeruer,</hi> as a <hi>Iustifier,</hi> and as a <hi>Glorifier.</hi> Next, vpon your ſelfe, who <pb n="74" facs="tcp:2857:33"/>haue offended him; being his creature, his houſehold ſeruant, his Chriſtian ſlaue; and one ſo deeply obliged, by his benefits. Thirdly, vpon the offences themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues which you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and be ſory at your hart, for hauing committed them; and
<note n="(r)" place="margin">For who can euer call to mind all his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſins.</note> if not in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler for them all, at leaſt for the
<note n="(h)" place="margin">He had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſinne; &amp; now he is but exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to renew his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for them:</note> moſt greiuous of them, which shall repreſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to your memory. Fourthly, vpon the good which you haue omitted; &amp; the tyme which you haue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2857:33"/>loſt; and the yeares that you haue miſpent. Fiftly, vpon the ſcandall which you haue giuen. And if any thing more be to be done; if
<note n="(t)" place="margin">We cannot be ſaued vnles firſt we make reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well of fame, as of goods if it lye in our power.</note> to make reſtitution, eyther of fame, or goods; if to pardon others, or to aske pardon your ſelf; reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and pardon, and aske pardon. If to perfourme any vowes, or fulfill any promiſes, performe, and fullfill them. Or finally, if you leaue any debts, or if you will make any ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of your repentance, <pb n="76" facs="tcp:2857:34"/>and pious end, you are now to put your hand to worke.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe thinges he offered himſelfe moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily; and did execute them all, with ſo great deuotion, that euery one now began, to change his ſtyle, in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to him. And finding, that whereas before, they thought they should haue to do but with a yong man, or rather but with a youth, and weakeling,
<note n="(u)" place="margin">He infinitly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> they were now to treate, with a manly, generous, and ripe Chriſtian (far ſuperiour to <pb n="77" facs="tcp:2857:34"/>that, which might perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture haue been expected of him) one of the <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatori,</hi> began with greate diſcretion, to diſcourſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the horrour of Death, which our moſt ſweete <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> did by his agony diſpoſſeſſe of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.
<q rend="margQuotes">Confide, ſaith he, and caſt your thoughts vpon him, and ſay, <hi>Pone
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Place me, O Lord, neere to thee, &amp; let the hand of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</note> me Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine iuxta te, &amp; cuiuſuis manus pugnet contra me.</hi>
               </q> And if now you find any bitter taſt in death in this short night, as without fayle you will,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2857:35"/>ſay, <hi>Pater
<note n="(y)" place="margin">O my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not as I will, but as thou wilt thy will be done.</note> mi, non ſicut ego; volo, ſed ſicut tu, fiat voluntas tua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The contrite Lord, made anſwere thus, <hi>The wickednes of my life doth fright, me, more, then the bitternes of my death O how wrechedly haue I ſpent theſe eighteene yeares? How ill haue I vnderstood my Sauiour? How vngratefull haue I beene for his noble fauours? How rebelliouſly haue I liued againſt his lawes? And now haue I run like a wild, vnbridled horſe, in theſe later yeares of mine; without any manner of <pb n="79" facs="tcp:2857:35"/>restraint, whereſoeuer the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſions, or conuerſations, or
<note n="(z)" place="margin">The ſinner; is only to blame himſelfe for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> rather (for I haue ſayd ill) whereſoeuer myne owne paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and blind affections, had a mind to plunge me? It is I, and none but I, who did precipitate me; and yet you bid me fixe my thoughts, and hopes vpon God; and ſay, Pone me Domine iuxta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, &amp; cuiuſuis manus pugnet contra me, fiat voluntas tua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon this, another of the <hi>Confortatori,</hi> did thus proceed.
<q rend="margQuotes">It is an acte of magnanimity, not to feare the angry face of death; &amp; <pb n="80" facs="tcp:2857:36"/>of humility, to acknowledge our offences; but of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to hope for pardon, as your Lordship doth; who well may ſay, <hi>Propter nome tuum Domine,</hi>
                  <hi>propitiabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris peccato meo, muitum eſt enim.</hi>
               </q> For thy names ſake O Lord thou shalt forgiue my ſin, for it is great. <hi>O how great,</hi> ſayd <hi>Signor Troilo? Euen as greate, after a manner, as is the mercy of God, which is immenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Proueditere</hi> then ſayd;
<q rend="margQuotes">Your Lordship, may, if you ſo be pleaſed, make <pb n="81" facs="tcp:2857:36"/>your laſt <hi>VVill,</hi> and
<hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> to the end that no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thought may ſollicite you, but of your ſoule alon.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Heereupon the <hi>Baron,</hi> without the leaſt delay, by way of anſwere, did bid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> write. And hauing taken out of his pocket, a little note, which he carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, he did ſuddainly dictate his
<hi>Teſtament;</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he deliuered ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers, which, in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are very conſiderable. Firſt,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations which may be made, vpon the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of penning his will.</note> of tender Deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; for he recommended his <pb n="82" facs="tcp:2857:37"/>ſoule to God, by moſt deare, and religious wordes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of Ripenes, which was more then of a young man; becauſe, in a moſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler manner, he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. Thirdly, of a moſt liuely Contrition; becauſe, with a moſt profound, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall affection of mind, he demaunded pardon of many, euen by name. Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thly, of great Magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; becauſe he coniured the Lady his Mother, that she would pardon all his aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes, <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2857:37"/>as he himſelfe did pardon them a thouſand tymes ouer. Beſeeching
<note n="(b)" place="margin">what a true, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an hart was this?</note> her, by a long, and chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an circuite of wordes, that she would neuer reſent his death; but he layd the fault vpon himſelfe, in al things. Fiftly, of Religious Piety; leauing large almes to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches, &amp; other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places; accommodating many poore
<note n="(c)" place="margin">This is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, much v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Italy.</note> Virgins, with dowryes, at the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer diſcretion, and to be performed by the care of his heyres; that God might
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2857:38"/>the rather haue mercy on him. Sixtly, of entiere Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; becauſe he tooke care, that euen more then was due by him, should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. Seauenthly, of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gratitude; becauſe he rewarded, whoſoeuer had done him any ſcruice in priſon. Eightly, of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuous Reuerence; becauſe he did in a moſt ſweet, and deere manner, aske pardon; of the Lady his Mother, &amp; of the reſt of his kinred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſids the expreſſing of other complements.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:2857:38"/>
            <p>Hauing ended his laſt <hi>VVill, VVell Syrs</hi> (ſayth he)
<hi>behold we haue this reſidue of tyme, now wholy free, for the care of our ſoule.</hi> And turning towards me, he ſayd, <hi>It
<note n="(d)" place="margin">He ſpeakes of his ſoule, for as much as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the guiding of it, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God.</note> is in your hand, and therefore diſpoſe of it; for this only is now, in my power to giue you.</hi> I then, by way of anſwere ſayd, Giue your ſelfe, my Lord, to IESVS.
<q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>I do ſo,</hi> ſayd he; and he ſayd it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly. And I againe, Giue your ſelfe wholy to him. He ſayd, <hi>I do.</hi> Conſecrate yourſelfe;</q> he ſtil ſayd, <hi>I do.</hi> 
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:2857:39"/>Make your ſelfe, ſayd I, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierely his.
<hi>But how</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>O Father, shall I make my ſelfe entierely his, if I be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and if perhaps, I be an enemy
<note n="(e)" place="margin">As al grieuous ſinners are, if they do not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which no man can be ſure that he hath ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently done, though he may haue great hope thereof.</note> of his.</hi> But in the meane tyme, whileſt the <hi>VVill</hi> was in writing, he that wrote it, put vs in mind, that it was to be publikely read; that ſo it might be shut vp, with a due
<note n="(f)" place="margin">A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, is not valide there, if it haue not ſeauen witneſſes at the leaſt.</note> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of witneſſes. And why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt this was in doing, that is, whyleſt the
<hi>Notary</hi> was reading of it; three thinges <pb n="87" facs="tcp:2857:39"/>of ſome conſideration did occurre. The firſt, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he read how he recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his ſoule to God, <hi>My body</hi> (ſayth he, (drawing neere me, according to his cuſtome) <hi>I diſpoſe not of; for now, it is no longer myne. It once was myne, and I would it had not beene ſo; but
<note n="(g)" place="margin">He acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, and iuſtice of God, in al things</note> it is more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon, that I hauing had ſo great care of it, in my life tyme, for my punishment, should not be ſuffered, to haue any power ouer it, now in my death. Let them therefore doe with it what they will; for I <pb n="88" facs="tcp:2857:40"/>ſacrifice it to God whatſoeuer it, be. Father, will not ſuch an oblation as this, doe me good?</hi> It will, ſaid I; without doubt it will; and what
<note n="(h)" place="margin">For he that giues his body, doth ſhew in good earneſt, that he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready giuen his ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le.</note> more acceptable oblation, can be made to our Lord, then that of the body? The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, That when the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies</hi> were read; it being obſerued, by the manner of expreſſing one of them, that he deliuered himſelfe as faulty, in a certaine thing, wherein indeed he was not ſo; and therefore the
<hi>VVill</hi> was to be redreſſed, as I <pb n="89" facs="tcp:2857:40"/>deſired, which ſerued not only, (as before) for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his conſcience, but for the ſauing alſo of his honour. Vpon this, putting off his
<hi>Montiera,</hi> or capp, <hi>O Father,</hi> ſaith he (and he did it halfe ſmiling) <hi>are you now taking care of my reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of the</hi> puntillios <hi>of Honour, and of that ſmoake or vanity of the world? Let my ſoule be ſaued, &amp; let al the vaine Honour perish, which I eyther had, or might haue had. Do you not remember that which euen
<note n="(i)" place="margin">This is not mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned heer before; but he ſaid alſo many other thinges which are not mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this ſhort
<hi>Relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note> now you ſayd,</hi> Mihi <pb n="90" facs="tcp:2857:41"/>mundus:
<note n="(k)" place="margin">The world is crucified to me, and I to it.</note> crucifixus eſt, &amp; ego mundo. <hi>In a word, let not the ſoule be touched, but let my Honour be blaſted, according to that accoumpt, which the blinde world is wont to make of Honour; that it may ſerue as a part of the punishement, which is due to me.</hi> The third, that at the ſame inſtant, his hat was brought him; and one of his people, being deſirous to take his <hi>Montie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> from off his head, <hi>what are you doing</hi> ſayth he? They anſwered, they would giue him his hat. But he bad
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2857:41"/>them let it alone, ſaying, <hi>That it imported not;</hi> and he added, with a ſoft voyce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Looke heer a whyle; they would faine honour this head of mine, which I am to looſe, within few houres, for my ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>VVill</hi> being then read, and shut; he throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe, as it were vpon me, with a moſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt kind of ſweetnes, ſaid, <hi>Father I am already reconciled; but I would faine make a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Confeſſion of my whole life, to your Reuerence. And althogh, ſince I came into priſon, I did <pb n="92" facs="tcp:2857:42"/>the ſame, in effect, at the inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of my Lady, my Mother; yet know, that I had then no light, or feeling of my ſinnes, in reſpect of that, which now I diſcouer in my hart. For, One thing it is, deare Father, for a man to confeſſe himſelfe, when he is in the ſight of death; and another, to do it not thinking of death; or at leaſt, but conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, as a far off.</hi> And ſo, calling for a
<note n="(l)" place="margin">There are eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wher to be had litle bookes, of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, wherby men are taught how to confeſſe their ſins exactly.</note> little booke, which he had aboue in the priſon (shewing a man the way, how to confeſſe his ſinnes, exactly well (which
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2857:42"/>his good MOTHER had
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought to him ſome dayes
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore) he began his
<hi>confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on.</hi> Wherin, my Lord God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth knowe, that, as it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awfull for me, by that moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mple authority, which himſelf gaue me, to declare as much therof, as I should thinke fit; ſo if I were able to expreſſe it, I ſay not, that
<hi>Rome</hi> would be aſtonished at it, but all <hi>Italy</hi> would be ſo. For if I ſpeake of the exact manner that he held; for as much as concerned the particuler deſcending <pb n="94" facs="tcp:2857:43"/>euen to idle wordes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anie other
<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> is no ſuch curſory or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall thing, as they which know it not, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, &amp; ſay.</note> ſuch littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing, me thought I wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hearing ſome well exerciſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religious man. In the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating of circumſtances<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the vnfolding of intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and intangled caſes, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was, as if he had bin ſome profound Deuine. In rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the determinate num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, &amp; the various kindes of his ſins; he made proofe of one, who had a moſt fresh, and happy memory.</p>
            <p>This rare Gentleman pawſing now and then, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2857:43"/>the Confeſſion of his ſinnes; and ſuffering certaine teares to fall qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly vpon my knees, he would be wiping them away; and that being done, he would often vſe to ſay with ſighes; <hi>O Father, how
<note n="(n)" place="margin">He had great reaſon to ſay ſo.</note> good hath our Lord been to me? Let him now be bleſsed, as often, and yet more often, then I haue offended him, in my former life.</hi> Why leſt he was accuſing himſelfe of his faults, he would expreſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine few, but they, all liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and moſt pious wordes;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2857:44"/>and in ſom particuler caſes ſo dearely tender; that, in his countenance, one might ſee euident ſignes, of how his very hart, was euen rent, within. So that between
<note n="(o)" place="margin">He pawſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes between both to reſthim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp; to recall his ſins, more freſhly to his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: for though it were inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, it was al but one <hi>Confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> till the <hi>Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> were giuen.</note> the times of his
<hi>confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the <hi>Confortatori,</hi> (doubting leaſt perhaps he might grow to faint) would be asking him if he needed not ſomewhat to reſtore, &amp; comfort him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. To which he anſwered (ſpeaking priuatly, &amp; more then once to me) <hi>This
<note n="(p)" place="margin">An admirable Contrition.</note> only comfort, or reſtoratiue I <pb n="97" facs="tcp:2857:44"/>would deſire; That my very hart might burſt for griefe; and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction might ſo be
<note n="(q)" place="margin">To the iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God; his ſorrow being dignified by the death &amp; paſſion, of Ieſus Chriſt, our Lord.</note> giuen, for my ſinnes, if perhaps euen that, would ſerue the turne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for as much as, to my thincking, he did melt as it were by ſo enlardging himſelfe in his <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> I had an eye vpon him, and I ventured to ſay thus vnto him.
<q rend="margQuotes">My deare <hi>Signor Troi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> be not ſo exceſſiuely cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and particuler, in accuſing your ſelfe; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of thoſe your former ſinnes,</q> which lye not now
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2857:45"/>vpon your ſoule. <hi>O
<note n="(r)" place="margin">See how truely this hart was tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for his ſins; and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelf.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>I haue waſted my whole life, in offending God; and will you haue me, or shall I content my ſelfe, in one ſingle houre, to demaund pardon of ſo many offences? So long in ſinning, and ſo short in confeſſing my ſinnes? That I am trouble ſome to you, my deare Father, I well diſcouer; but what can I doe withall, if I be forced to it?</hi> And heer againe, he began to make for himſelfe, a very bath of teares. And inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretinge what I had ſaid, after his owne conceite, <pb n="99" facs="tcp:2857:45"/>he added, with teares re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled, <hi>And this alſo do my ſinnes deſerue, by way of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, that hauing cast ſo much, and ſo much time away, in preiudice of my ſaluation, I should now want time, wherein I might euen confeſſe my ſinnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pardon me, deare Father, and endure this trouble for the loue of God; for you shall
<note n="(s)" place="margin">To do a good worke by the grace, &amp; for the loue of God, is merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; for ſo Chriſt our Lord hath made it.</note> merit, in his ſight, by helping this poore ſoule of mine, towards ſaluation; &amp; I will remaine with obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to you, when I shall go by the mercy of God &amp; your good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, into the place of rest.</hi> And <pb n="100" facs="tcp:2857:46"/>finding that ſtill he grew in teares, I confeſſe my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for I was not able to containe my ſelfe, from expreſſing alſo tendernes, by teares.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as he percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this, he ſaid; <hi>Father, your Reuerence weepes, and yet you weepe not for your ſelfe, but for me; and yet you will not haue me weepe, for my ſelfe.</hi> But then, both of vs being ſilent for a time, he after, began againe to confeſſe, with thoſe accuſtomed short words, but full of ſubſtance, <pb n="101" facs="tcp:2857:46"/>and propriety; making me write down al thoſe things, which he confided to me, for the diſchardge of his conſcience. Whileſt I was writinge, he would needes for his contentment hold the Standish, in his owne hands; and read thoſe lines, when I had done; and kiſſe them, and then bath them in teares.</p>
            <p>But of nothing did he accuſe himſelfe ſo much, as of all that, which had any relation to the Lady, his Mother. Nor am I able by
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2857:47"/>any meanes to expreſſe, with what aboundance of teares, he accompanied thoſe accuſations of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For, beginning euen from his very Infancy, <hi>Father</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>I
<note n="(t)" place="margin">A lardge expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable greife he had, for his diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and in gratitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to the Lady his mother.</note> haue committed many offences againſt God; yet at this tyme, me thinks, I am not ſo much afflicted for any thing, as for not hauing knowne, how to ſerue my ſelfe, of that tender loue, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and patience, which my Lady my Mother, expreſſed, in the education of me. For euen when I was yet a child, she gaue <pb n="103" facs="tcp:2857:47"/>me in charge, to certaine learned and religious Preceptours; who till I arriued to haue ſixteene yeares of age, did with great fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and ſufficiency, teach me, not only the litterature of</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, <hi>but</hi> Philoſophy
<hi>alſo. And ſo did they further shew, how I was to addreſſe my ſelfe towardes piety, by their good example, and aduice. Nor yet content with this; how ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous was she alſo, to procure by many other meanes, that I might proceed, both in</hi> Learning, <hi>and</hi> Vertue? <hi>For
<note n="(u)" place="margin">See heer the Image, of a holy and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> concerning that of</hi> Learning, <hi>she gaue me <pb n="104" facs="tcp:2857:48"/>ſtore of bookes, of tyme, of opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and a thouſand tender fauours she did me, which were conuenient for thoſe yeares of myne. And for the inducing me to</hi> Vertue, <hi>she addreſſed me to choyce of good Conuerſations, ſpirituall Diſcourſes, excellent Sermons, and Perſons, who might from tyme to tyme giue me counſaile. Commanding me, and cauſing me to be lead to</hi> Confeſſion; <hi>not only vpon all the principall Feastes of the yeare, but once moreouer euery moneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And, till this very tyme, <pb n="105" facs="tcp:2857:48"/>when I am ſpeaking to your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, you may, if you will take the paynes, find among my papers, moſt euident testimonyes of what now I am ſaying; and eſpecially
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Note the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences which this holy mother did vſe, for the pious educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> a short manner of Instruction, how to ſpend the whole day, well. The thinges beſides whereof she did admonish me, were in a manner, infinite. VVhen I was yet a little one, she kept me in bridle, by threates, yea and by ſtroakes ſometymes; and when I was growne elder, she endeauoured to do it, by the faire meanes, of requeſts, and promiſes; and oftentymes, with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2857:49"/>ſo many teares, as that now, they are as many launces to paſſe through my hart. For this, did she procure that
<note n="(y)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippo Nerio,</hi> was his Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. The <hi>Chieſa Noua</hi> was a new Church, wherein God was ſerued by him and his. I do not ordinarily tranſlate theſe names, out of Italian, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are proper, either to perſons, or places.</note> bleſſed man</hi> Philippo, <hi>of the</hi> Chieſa noua <hi>to aſſiſte, and hold me, when I was</hi> confirmed;
<hi>and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward I should make particuler friendship with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She kept me far off from loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon ill examples; and held me neere her ſelfe, after the manner, as I may ſay, of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious life; exhorting me often, day and night, that I would liue <pb n="107" facs="tcp:2857:49"/>Nobly,
<note n="(z)" place="margin">True Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, is true No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</note> and like a Chriſtian. Nor did that bleſſed mouth of hers, euer ceaſe to ſay,</hi> Troi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, my Sonne, feare God, &amp; loue God.
<hi>For this did she take vpon her, the gouernement of all my</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtella</hi> in Itálian, doth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify both the manſion houſe, and the Towne, or vilage belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to it.</note> Caſtles; <hi>and the care of all my affaires; liuing in a continuall ſtate, of between hope, and feare, of the proofe that I would made. Nor was there a</hi> Religious Houſe, <hi>or</hi> Monaſtery, <hi>to the prayers wherof, she reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended me not Nor came there any Religious perſons to her, nor did she meet with any abroad, to whome, all
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2857:50"/>forgettefull of her ſelfe, she would not ſay,</hi> Pray
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Som body prayed ſo well for him, as to make him a Saint.</note> for my Sonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I, vngratefull to her ſo great labours, when I grew to haue ſixteene yeares of age, did render her, ſo ill payment, for ſuch a huge ſumme of loue; as that I euen parted houſe with her; &amp; did outrage her, both by wordes, and deeds; in ſuch ſort, as that the vttermoſt of all punishment, ſeemeth a hundred times leſſe to me, then my deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And when, deare Father, I thincke vpon the teares with she was euer sheading for me, <pb n="109" facs="tcp:2857:50"/>both by day, and in thoſe nights, ſo ſadly ſpent; and on the ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes which she ſuffered vpon my occaſion, I find contentment, in that I am to dye; whereby, me thinckes, I grow, in part, to ouershaddowe, ſo many of my lewd behauiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither
<note n="(c)" place="margin">The inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue of this Mother, to her Sonne.</note> yet, after I had ſeparated my ſelfe from her, did she giue ouer to ſollicite me with notes, and letters, and meſſages, and a thouſand other inuentions, that I would be induced to retire my ſelfe from vitious conuerſations; and she wold pray me, &amp; importune me,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2857:51"/>&amp; coniure me, that I would take to good. And well I know, that no kind of deuotion was omitted by her, for my reformation, both by viſiting as many</hi> Churches, <hi>and</hi> Religious perſons, <hi>as she knew in Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in fine, she came often to me, both by day and night, whileſt I was wandering vp and downe in ſuch company; and
<note n="(d)" place="margin">It ſeems to haue been a kind of ſtrife &amp; war, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene how kind, a Mother could tel how to be, and how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind a sonne.</note> when she found me out, she would caſt her ſelfe, euen at my feete, that ſo I might once be drawen to open mine eyes, and would conſider the precipice that I was approaching to; and the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2857:51"/>ruines, beſides the shame, that would ineuitably come vpon me; and that I would returne to Chriſt; and that once, I would truly weigh (for theſe were her very wordes)</hi> whoſe Sonne I was; <hi>and that I would conſider, what thing that was, which euer had beene wanting to me, that ſo, in that deſperate fashion, I should abandone all care of my Eſtate, of my Life, and of my Honour. And vſually she acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed theſe admonitions, and requeſts of hers, with moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der teares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sometimes againe, she would <pb n="112" facs="tcp:2857:52"/>turne aſide, and caſting vp he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eyes to God, she would beſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him, either to conuert me, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> els
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Her prayer was hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in a better, though in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then ſhe moſt deſired.</note> to take me to himſelfe. And this I can ſay with al truth, that euen from the beginning, to this very houre, wherein now I liue, she hath neuer ceaſed to procure my ſaluation. For euen from the firſt tyme, that she
<note n="(f)" place="margin">She was in Rome at his commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſaw how the world would go with him, ſhe retyred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, with her load of ſorrow.</note> came to ſee me heere in priſon, she exhorted me to</hi> Confeſſion, <hi>and euer ſince, she hath come, as thicke as haile vpon me, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes with Religious men, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:2857:52"/>ſometymes with pious Books. So long, that now at laſt, I am by the fauour of God, returned a little into my ſelfe. And beſides the cutting off, of all occaſions of doing il, she gaue me many great opportunityes of good; beſides the exhortations, which she her ſelfe made to me, in moſt feruent manner, that I would reſtore my ſelfe, to the ſeruice of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor could euer any Sonne deſire any fauour, or content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Mother, which myne, did not, of her ſelfe, impart to me. And I, on the other ſide, haue ſerued, but to make her life <pb n="114" facs="tcp:2857:53"/>moſt vnfortunate, by this period of myne. I beſeech our Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue me, &amp; to receaue the future affliction of her hart, in preſent diſcount of my offences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then towardes the end of his Confeſſion; <hi>I deſire</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>a fauour of you now, deare Father, which you muſt not deny me. It is, that I may haue liberty to lament my ſinnes with teares; and that, by them, I may giue teſtimony to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſty, of the
<note n="(g)" place="margin">That ſo the penitent himſelfe by fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, might haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of comfort.</note> griefe, wherewith my harte aboundes within.</hi> Weepe out, ſayd I, ſince our Lord doth giue
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2857:53"/>you ſuch a deſire of wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
            <p>I had ſcarce brought forth this laſt worde, when allready, there beganne to fall, a moſt aboundant showre of teares from his eyes; in ſuch ſort,
<note n="(h)" place="margin">An admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and almoſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> as that he bathed a good part of one of my armes; and my ſleeue was as wett through, as if it had rayned from aboue. Which accident I obſeruing, after ſome halfe quarter of an houre; and doubting, leaſt his hart might ſo diſcharg it ſelfe by <pb n="116" facs="tcp:2857:54"/>his eyes, rather for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion which he might haue of death, then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe;
<q rend="margQuotes">I deſired, that for the loue of
<hi>Ieſus,</hi> he would quiet himſelfe, &amp; not mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply his affliction, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to torment his mind,</q> in that manner. To this he anſwered; <hi>Father, I giue you my fayth, that I do not, at all, be wayle my death; but I do on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and purely, lament the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which I haue committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Almighty God. And
<note n="(i)" place="margin">A happy coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſorrow, with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</note> I haue ſo much hope, in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of my deare Lord, that not <pb n="117" facs="tcp:2857:54"/>only I shall shead no teares, for my death; but not ſo much as change my countenance. Father, I bewayle my moſt vnfortunate life, and not my moſt happy death. That life was, indeed, moſt vnfortunate; whereas this death, is moſt happy; for in fine, if in that, I liued an enemy to God, I hope, in this, I shall dye his friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Well then, ſayd I, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in your
<hi>Confeſſion,</hi> that ſo you may dye the friend of God; and lay, a part of your tears, aſide, the whyle.</q> Whereupon. The moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2857:55"/>young Gentleman, accommodatinge himſelfe to my direction, did iuſt proceed, where he had left.</p>
            <p>At this I wondred ſo much themore; for as much as I my ſelfe had forgotten it, though I alſo had one of thoſe little bookes in my hand, which inſtruct how a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> may be well made. But he going on, did lay before me, (as if it had bin in one ſingle proſpect) the whole courſe of his life; with ſo great clarity, and breuity, that I found my
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2857:55"/>ſelfe, as obliged, to aske him, if during many dayes before, he had not applied himſelfe to make ſuch a preparation. To which the yong Noble man made this very anſwere: <hi>So great is the light (as I haue already inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) which my deare Lord Ieſus vouchſafes to giue me at this inſtant, of my whole life, that euen whyleſt I am confeſsing, me thinkes I behold all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<note n="(k)" place="margin">This was a very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall fauous of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</note> as in a glaſſe; and I read all my thoughtes, and wordes, as in a booke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, without doubt, <pb n="120" facs="tcp:2857:56"/>ſo it was. For he, without euer, miſtaking a worde, did ſo call all his ſinnes to minde, that by that time he wanted little of hauing declared them al diſtinctly. Only at the very end, as it were, of his <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> he returned to repeate ſome thinges which he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid; and I doubting that he did ſo, as hauing forgotten what he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed before, I told him of that inaduertence (as I reputed it,) when yet he made me this anſwere: <hi>I
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2857:56"/>know well, deare Father, that I repeate ſome thinges; but I do it, to the end that I may now more perfectly detest them, &amp; be confounded in my ſelfe. And eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<note n="(l)" place="margin">How deſirous this ſoule was, to make God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends.</note> ſince I haue paſſed the greateſt part of my life in ſuch thinges as theſe, to the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our Lord, I do now for the better pleaſing of him, paſſe this tyme of my death, in a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking remembrance of the ſame. And if it be troubleſome to your Reuerence, as I know it is, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to heare my ſo many offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; do you remember once for all, that this ſoule, is, of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2857:57"/>for whome Chriſt dyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Nay ſaid I, if your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, haue any ſuch appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, you may repeate as much, and as often as it pleaſeth you; for I only aduiſed you of it before, as thinking that perhaps you might haue done it by er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</q> 
               <hi>The errour</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>was myne, and a grieuous errour it was, to offend them ſo many wayes, who did euer stand in my defence. But howſoeuer that be; in this reſpect, as in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I shall dye contented, in that I can neuer ſatisfy my ſelfe,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2857:57"/>with cofeſſing my faults to you, deare Father. VVhich now, by the goodnes of God, are as well knowne by me, as heeretofore they were little eſteemed; &amp; are now as bitterly lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, as heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore they gaue me guſt, though it were a falſe one. I
<note n="(m)" place="margin">The man did euen melt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene griefe &amp; loue.</note> wish, Othou moſt ſweet Sauiour of my ſoule, that I had, as wel, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand tongues, that ſo I might fully confeſſe them; a thouſand eyes, that ſo, I might bitterly bewayle them; and a thouſand harts, that ſo, eternally I might detest them. And that this grief for my ſinnes, committed againſt <pb n="124" facs="tcp:2857:58"/>God, might ſo breake my hart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the inſtrument of Iuſtice, will take my head, for them, which I haue committed concerning men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I do, good Father, (by the goodnes of God) know what a ſinner I am. As a ſinner, I lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t my ſelfe, and as a ſinner I will dye, but a ſinner, all humbled, &amp; contrite; and with my teares I will make my Funeralls; then ſuffer me to performe them, after myne owne fashion.</hi> And heer cuen I, not
<note n="(n)" place="margin">I cannot blame him,</note> being able to containe my ſelfe from wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, he obſerued it, and ſaid thus.
<hi>Moſt happy Funerals <pb n="125" facs="tcp:2857:58"/>are therfore theſe of mine, which are ſolemnized by the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God. Yet this part belonges not to you, but only as being a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to my ſoule. VVho knowes, but that by theſe mutuall teares, and this exchange of tendernes, my impure conſcience may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be cleanſed?</hi> Thus both of vs, being ſilent for a while, he then proceeded: <hi>VVell, my good Father, it is now high time, that by the
<note n="(o)" place="margin">This authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, was giuen to his true Church by Ieſus Chriſt our Lord; &amp; in his name, &amp; by his power, it is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</note> Authority, which God hath giuen you,</hi> to looſe, and bind men <hi>on earth, you looſe me, from ſo many chaines of ſinns,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:2857:59"/>which hang vpon me. To the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that, as you haue taught me,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may ſay,</hi> Auditui meo dabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gaudium &amp; laetitiam, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultabunt oſſa humiliata
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>And firſt do you giue me</hi> Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, <hi>and then, I may perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me my</hi> Pennance.
<hi>Though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what</hi> Pennance, <hi>carrying proportion to my ſinnes, is your</hi> Reuerence <hi>able to impoſe.</hi> At this, he caſt himſelfe at my feete, and bowed his head to my knee, where I had layd my left hand; and he all bathed it with teares, and kiſſed it; and expected
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2857:59"/>the <hi>Penance</hi> and <hi>Abſolution.</hi> Which I gaue him, fully, in forme of a
<note n="(p)" place="margin">This is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant merits of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, to the ſoules which ſtand in need thereof.</note> 
               <hi>Plenary Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biley,</hi> according to the moſt ample priuiledges,
<note n="(q)" place="margin">By the Popes.</note> which are granted to them of that <hi>Congregation,</hi> which is called of the
<note n="(r)" place="margin">It is called a congregation of
<hi>Miſericordia,</hi> becauſe it is ſo great a worke of charity &amp; mercy wherupon they imploy themſelues.</note> 
               <hi>Miſericordia.</hi> Being abſolued, and hauing done his <hi>Pennance,</hi> with incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affection of mind, he ſate downe againe by my direction; and then, the reſt did come, and circle him in round about, after <pb n="128" facs="tcp:2857:60"/>the accuſtomed manner.</p>
            <p>I then ſpake firſt to him after this ſort:
<q rend="margQuotes">Moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord
<hi>Troilo,</hi> our <hi>Bleſſed Saniour</hi> IESVS <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whom here we haue preſent, did, by dying vpon the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> gine remedy, in his perſon, this night, to three thinges, amongſt many others. He
<note n="(s)" place="margin">An applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion full of life &amp; comfort.</note> dyed, in the flower, &amp; vigour of his youth; that your Lordship, might not haue too much tendernes, &amp; compaſſion of your owne tender youth, and ſo might ſay, <hi>O, but why is my life taken
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2857:60"/>away in ſo tender years?</hi> And this is the firſt. He dyed, and he dyed of a violent death; that to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe it might not ſeeme inſupportable, to dye vpon neceſſity, and ſo you might ſay,
<hi>O, but why is the flower of my yeares, cut off by a violent hand?</hi> and this is the ſecond. He dyed of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull death, which in thoſe times was inflicted; that it might not ſeeme ſtrang to your Lordship, to dye by the hand of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and ſo you might ſay,
<hi>O, <pb n="130" facs="tcp:2857:61"/>but why died not I in my cradle, or at leaſt by ſome other natural accident?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Nay, if your Lordship will accept this death, in ſo tender yeares, you offer him the beſt part of your tyme. By dying of a violent death, you may make that which is neceſſary, to be voluntary; and by dying of a dishonourable death, (ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it as a Pennance for your ſinnes) you may fly the shame, of that laſt terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day. And ſo much the better, you may accept ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <pb n="131" facs="tcp:2857:61"/>for that you are not to dye in publique, vpon the Bridge, as the ordinary Cuſtome beares; but
<note n="(t)" place="margin">It is there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of leſſe diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to be put priuatly to death. They who dye priuatly, dye within the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, they who pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kely, at the foot of the Bridge.</note> priuately heere below, in the Court, as is wont to be vſed, towards your Peeres. I added alſo ſome other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, &amp; ſo ended my ſpeach. To which the
<hi>Baro,</hi> who was euer ready, made this anſwere.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And
<note n="(u)" place="margin">How wiſe, the grace of God, is able to make a very yong man, vpon a ſuddaine.</note> I, O Father, for as much as concernes the firſt, dye willingly in this fresh age of myne; becauſe thus I shalbe ſure <pb n="132" facs="tcp:2857:62"/>not to offend my Lord, any more. And, from this inſtant, I offer him my yeares, my age, &amp; my life; and a hundred yeares, and a hundred ages, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred liues. As for the ſecond; I will make a vertue of neceſſity; and being to dye perforce, and according to reaſon; I will dye willingly, that ſo I may yield willingly, vnto force, &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly giue ſatisfaction to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But as for the third; I could wish for a more ignominious death. And be you pleaſed to know, that to haue dyed in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique, would haue giuen me I <pb n="133" facs="tcp:2857:62"/>know not what increaſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, &amp; guſt. For ſo I might haue hoped by
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe publike ſinnes, require publike ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> publique Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to haue made a better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes, for my publique crimes. And God doth know, that I take no contentment, to receaue the fauour of dying priuately. But yet howſoeuer, if the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which is made, be ſuch; I reſiſt it not. Our Lord will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the promptitude of my wil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heereupon, the <hi>Proue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditore</hi> tooke vp the ſpeach, and ſayd:
<q rend="margQuotes">Let your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship accommodate it ſelfe, to the will, and prouidence <pb n="134" facs="tcp:2857:63"/>of God; who hath not only one way, of ariuing to ſaue our ſoules, nor one only means of drawing them to him. He leadeth one by one meanes, and others by another. It importeth not that
<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſecret but they are all iuſt.</note> his Iudgmentes be hidden from vs, but it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth that they are iuſt. Who can tell, if your Lordship should haue dyed in any other ſort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, whether or no, you should haue bin ſaued?</q> 
               <hi>I am he</hi> (ſayth the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron) <hi>who can tell you that; for I should haue tumbled headlong into hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:2857:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Do you not know how God hath proceeded with me? It is iuſt as a Hunteſ-man would do, when he would take a wild beast, but he would haue him brought to his hand, whole, and ſound; and not to be torne by the teeth or pawes of doggs; nor strocken by the bow, nor bruized by nets, or ſnares. He driues this beaſt, ſometymes one way, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes another; but neuer lets ſlip the doggs, nor diſchargeth the arrow; nor ſpreads he the net, or Toyle vpon the ground, or ſets the ſnare; but, at the most, with ſome outcryes, or els <pb n="136" facs="tcp:2857:64"/>by throwing of ſome ſtones, he rowſeth him, and addreſſeth him towardes the place deſigned; &amp; ſo long doth he driue the beaſt by ſeuerall wayes, that, at last, he bringes him thither, where he would haue him. The Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſ-man knowes this well; and did long expect him there; &amp; he takes him, and enioyes him, all ſound, and ſafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Note how wittily, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes this applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to himſelf.</note> he, O my Good Ieſus, who haue beene this beaſt, hunted hither, and thither; but thou hadſt a mind, to haue me ſafe; thou hadſt a mind to haue me ſound. And ſo thou didſt not <pb n="137" facs="tcp:2857:64"/>permit, that I should be torne with dogs, nor pierced by arrow, nor taken by nets, or Toyles, or ſnares; when thou deliueredſt me out of ſo many dangers of death, in which, though very young, I haue found my ſelfe; &amp; wherin, if I had dyed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faile, I had perished for all eternity. Thou didſt only throw ſtones at me, and thou cryedſt out after me, when by ſo many admonitions, and inſpirations, thou didſt ſolicite me. And now I repent my ſelfe, that I was ſo deafe to them. But what mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, if I were deafe, who after <pb n="138" facs="tcp:2857:65"/>a ſort was
<note n="(a)" place="margin">By ſinne</note> dead? And thus hath his goodnes conducted me to this ſtraite pace, without my knowing of it; that ſo I may be forced to leap into his lapp. For whither am I able to turne my ſelfe more ſecurely, then to my deare Ieſus? Yea, and yet, if I were able; I would not turne, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way but to him. It is true, that I am forced; but yet I am content withall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the <hi>Confortatori</hi> then replied:
<q rend="margQuotes">It is inough, <hi>Signor Troilo.</hi> So great, and ſo liberall, is the goodnes of God, that he accepteth all,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:2857:65"/>and he doth it with delight.</q> And one of the
<hi>Chieſa nuoua</hi> ſaid;
<q rend="margQuotes">That although our Lord receaued a
<hi>Precept,</hi> or <hi>Commandment</hi> that he should dye; yet neuertheleſſe it is affirmed, &amp; it is true, that he dyed
<hi>voluntarily.</hi>
               </q> And hauing accompanied this ſpeach of his, with diuers choice examples, one of our Fathers shut vp that diſcourſe, with shewing, by what means, that which was <hi>neceſſary,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">That puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is impoſed by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, may be made volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> might ſo grow to be <hi>voluntary,</hi> by <hi>a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> accepting of it: and, that <pb n="140" facs="tcp:2857:66"/>ſo much more, it would be <hi>meritorious,</hi> as it should more <hi>willingly</hi> be imbraced. <hi>Then teach me</hi> (ſayd the <hi>Baron</hi>) <hi>how I may make this neceſſary death truly voluntary.</hi> And then certaine deuout, and apt waies how to do it, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, by the <hi>Gouernour</hi> of the
<hi>Congregation</hi> of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortatori,</hi> and imbraced by the
<hi>Baron,</hi> I ſaid;
<q rend="margQuotes">Perhaps <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> we weary you to much.</q> 
               <hi>How can you weary me?</hi> ſaid he. <hi>Theſe diſcourſes, make the night short to me, and they make my diſaſtre, fortunat.</hi> 
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:2857:66"/>And heere, all were ſilent for a while; when he riſing vp (for he was ſitting) ſaid, <hi>That he would ſpeake with the Father.</hi> And drawing neere me, the
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the patient, did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</note> 
               <hi>Confortatore</hi> ſaid the <hi>Confiteor;</hi> &amp;, that being ended, <hi>I deſire</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if it pleaſe you, Father, to call againe to mind, ſome of the things aforſaid; both for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter repetition of them, &amp; for the additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome others.</hi> Which I refuſing, out of the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance I had, that it was not neceſſary, he ſaid; <hi>And it is poſſible, deare Father, that you
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:2857:67"/>will not giue me this laſt content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? VVill you not permitt, at leaſt, that I may ſatiſſiy my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with confeſſing the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which I haue committed againſt God? And beſides, doth not your Reuerence remember, that we muſt ſpeake togeather of</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">The Father it ſeems had made him ſom ſuch promiſe before.</note> pennance? And I anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Let that
<hi>Pennance</hi> be, to dye, and to dye well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then teach me that,</hi> (ſaid he.) And I, thus to him:
<q rend="margQuotes">Offer now, this death of yours, to God, with your whole hart, in pennance, for the ſinnes with you
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:2857:67"/>haue committed.</q> 
               <hi>I do</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>offer it with my hart, and with my mouth; and it grieues me, (as our Lord doth know) that I haue not, this night, a thouſand heades, that in this one of mine, they might be al cut off, and a thouſand liues, that they might all be loſt. Nay
<note n="(e)" place="margin">How much doth he giue to God; &amp; how little doth he thinke it to be: &amp; yet how faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it all to be of God.</note> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and know, that euen that pennance, would yet fall short; but ſince more I cannot, more I know not what to do; and ſince more I haue not, I can giue no more; and euen the doing, and giuing, of this little, do I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, to proceede from
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:2857:68"/>the hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I told him, by the way of reply, that it was well; and that he should ſtill be doing ſo.
<q rend="margQuotes">And when (ſayd I) you are laying your head vpon the blocke, ſay thus in your hart. O Lord, by this act of myne, I proteſt, to do pennance for my ſins, as if I had a thouſand heads and a thouſand liues; and I acknowledge, and confeſſe, that it is all but little. But I doubt <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then, you will be able to remember this; for then <pb n="145" facs="tcp:2857:68"/>perhapps you willbe, as it were, not your ſelf. It is no trifle to looke death in the face, take my word for that. The magnanimous Lord made this anſwere.</q> 
               <hi>I wil not preſume ſo much vpon my ſelfe, but I
<note n="(f)" place="margin">He can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faile who putteth all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God, &amp; none in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</note> hope well, and confide greatly in God, that he will not let it fall out of my memory. And if, by many accident, you should perceaue that I were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of ſo great a grace, doe me the fauour to bring me in mind of it; for you shall find me ready to put it in execution. In the meane whyle, I beſeech your <pb n="146" facs="tcp:2857:69"/>Reuerence tell me ſomewhat els towardes this end of myne, and that quickly, for the tyme hath winges.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">I bad him leaue the care of that to me. For I wil (ſayd I) go intimating from time to tyme, whatſoeuer you are to thinke vpon; &amp; whatſoeuer you shall be to ſay, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> til your laſt breath.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">And
<note n="(g)" place="margin">He exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him to a great deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his good Angell.</note> very now, you shall begin to make a ſtrait friendship with your <hi>Good Angell.</hi> And firſt aske pardon of him with your hart, for the little gratitude which you haue expreſſed,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:2857:69"/>for the Cuſtody that he hath affoarded you; which hath binſo inceſſant, ſo pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, ſo diligent, &amp; ſo full of loue.</q> Vpon which wordes, he ſayd (caſting himſelfe vpon his knees;)
<hi>Yea, not only with my mouth, but with my hart, I begge pardon of him, for the much, and much ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which I haue vſed, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding his ſo great beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity, and loue to me;</hi> and ſo kiſſing my knee, he ſate downe againe. So that I proceeded, and ſaid:
<q rend="margQuotes">Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then with your ſelfe,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:2857:70"/>that your
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Saint Hierome ſayth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſoule hath an <hi>Augaius Cuſtos</hi> aſſigned to it by Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, from the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the birth till the laſt of life. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Hier. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>conc. in</hi> 18. <hi>cap. Matt.</hi> The holy Scriptures and holy Fathers doe alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in proofe of the miniſtery of Angella in the help of men.</note> 
                  <hi>good Angel</hi> now is heer, who euen from your very firſt beginning, when you were borne, &amp; ſo much more at this houre, which is ſo full of danger, doth aſſiſt you, and eſpecially, in ſix particulers. Firſt, he hinders the impetuous aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the diuell, and weakens the force of all thoſe maligne ſpirits, who do, at this inſtant, conſpire to the damnation of your ſoule. Secondly, he brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes <pb n="149" facs="tcp:2857:70"/> into your hart, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, Generoſity, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, and Contrition. Thirdly, he lightneth this Darcknes, this Anguish, &amp; this Death. Fourthly, with great ſollicitude, he carrieth foreward, and backward, thoſe meſſages, which paſſe betweene God and you; he gathers vp your ſighs, your very countenances, and the humiliations of your hart; there is not one of them, which he ſuffereth to looſe his way. Fiftly, he negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with other Angells of <pb n="150" facs="tcp:2857:71"/>ſuperiour
<note n="(i)" place="margin">We read in holy ſcripture (<hi>Daniel</hi> 10.) how one An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, for the good of men; &amp; both the holy Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do euery where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, with ſhewing the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der care that the holy Angells haue of all thinges, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne vs, either in ſoule, body, or goods.</note> Quiers, ſo to procure effectual aſſiſtances for your ſaluation. In moſt particuler manner, he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth <hi>S. Michael</hi> the <hi>Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell,</hi> that he will defend you in this night. Sixtly, he ſolliciteth my good Angell alſo, that he may procure me to be a competent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, in this paſſage, which you are making to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes your ſaluation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Salute him therfore, and ſay thus with me; <hi>Angele Dei,</hi> 
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:2857:71"/>O
<note n="(k)" place="margin">He ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the prayer which Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſay dayly, &amp; more often then ſo, to their good Angell:
<hi>Angele Dei, qui cuſtos es mei, me tibi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſum, pietate ſuperna, hodie il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumina, cuſtodi, rege, guberna.</hi> O thou Angell of God, who art my keeper, appointed by the goodnes of God, illuminate me, this day, preſerue me, rule and gouerne me. Amen.</note> thou Angell of God, ſo ill knowne, and ſo ill vſed by me, <hi>qui cuſtos es mei,</hi> who keepeſt me, with ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual care, and perfect loue, <hi>me tibi commiſſum,</hi> who am committed to thee, being a man ſo faulty, and brought by the prouidence of God to this paſſage; but yet a ſinner who by his mercy, &amp; thy prayers is contrite for his ſinnes, <hi>pietate ſuperna,</hi> by the goodnes of God, for <pb n="152" facs="tcp:2857:72"/> I find no deſert, but do cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially confeſſe much deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>in hac morte, &amp; hac nocte,</hi> in this death, which is due to me for my offences, &amp; in this laſt period of my life, <hi>illumina, custodi, rege, &amp; gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berna,</hi> do thou illuminate, defend, protect, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne me, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </q> This good Noble Man, did repeate theſe wordes, with affectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and abundant teares; &amp; euen by his countenance, one might ſee, his very hart ſplit in his body. And not contenting himſelfe, to ſay <pb n="153" facs="tcp:2857:72"/>it only once, he would needs repeate it then, three times; and afterwardes, he did it againe, ſo much more often, the ſame night, as that all the times ariued, I thinke, to ten; letting me know withall, that he had not felt greater ſolace, and guſt, in any one ſpirituall exerciſe, then in this.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Secondly (ſayd I) you shal take the Glorious Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, for your
<note n="(l)" place="margin">To pray for him, as one man may do for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; though all the Saints, &amp; much more, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Mother of God, do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, in a far more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent manner.</note> interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour; and then <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>S. Paul,</hi> who were both, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned to the <pb n="154" facs="tcp:2857:73"/> loſſe of their heads, as your Lordship is.</q> 
               <hi>It is true</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>that they were condemned as I am; but with this difference, That they ſuffered innocent, &amp; I for my faults; and therefore I I accuſe my ſelfe, of ſuch, and ſuch, and ſuch offences, which I haue committed againſt God. VVhich howſoeuer I confeſſed before, yet for the reaſons which I haue already touched, I do wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly repeate the ſame.</hi> After he had ended his
<hi>Confeſsion,</hi> and receaued <hi>Abſolution</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his knees, I deſired him to ſit down againe, that the <pb n="155" facs="tcp:2857:73"/>wonted company might come about him.</p>
            <p>And euer, ſome one of them, would be taking vp, ſome verſe of the <hi>holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> which might be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the preſent occaſion. As for example, <hi>Viam iniquitatis amoue à me, &amp; de lege tua miſerere mei. Suſcipe ſeruum tuum in bonum, &amp; iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficationes tuas edoce me. Bonum mihi, quia humiliaſti me, vt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam iuſtificationes tuas. Cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui Domine, quia aequitas iudicia tua, &amp; in veritate tua humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime. Fiat cor meum immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:2857:74"/>in iuſtificationibus tuis, vt non confundar. Miferere mei Deus, ſecundum magnam miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiam tuam, &amp; ſecundum multitudinem miſerationum tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum, dele iniquitatem meam. Erraui ficut ouis quae perijt, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſeruum tuum Domine. Deus propitius eſto mihi peccatori. Deus in adiutorium meum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende.</hi> And a hundred other, ſuch as theſe; which now, and then, were declared by ſome one of
<note n="(m)" place="margin">The <hi>Reſigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> men declared them, though the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortatori</hi> might repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them.</note> vs, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the preſent occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherin he tooke much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:2857:74"/>
            <p>But
<note n="(n)" place="margin">He was moſt tenderly deuoted to the B. Virgin.</note> eſpecially he had great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, in vſing theſe other Iaculatory Prayers, <hi>Maria mater gratiae, Mater miſericordiae, Tu nos ab hoſte protege, &amp; hora mortis ſuſcipe;</hi> repeating often theſe laſt wordes, <hi>&amp; hora mortis ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe.</hi> And againe; <hi>Eiaergo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocata noſtra, illos tuos miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes oculos ad nos conuerte, &amp; Ieſum benedictum fructum ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris tui, mihi, poſt hanc noctem, oſtende, O clemens, O pia, O dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Virgo Maria. Ora pro me peccatore indigno, in hac hora mortis meae, Amen, Amen, Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <pb n="158" facs="tcp:2857:75"/>Recordare Ieſu pie, Quod ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cauſa tuae viae, Ne me perdas ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> die &amp;c.</hi> In this exerciſe, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> brothers, of the <hi>Congregati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the <hi>Miſericordia,</hi> were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perfect, and diſcreete; deliuering out, in fit times, a greate number of theſe verſicles, without impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuning, or perplexing him. And ſo alſo did other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men, according to the occaſion, without either interrupting the one the other, or yet ouerweariyng the yong Noble Man; and they alſo brought thinges <pb n="159" facs="tcp:2857:75"/>ſo, as to accompany them with certaine motiues, and conſiderations, with bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, but with great life of deuotion.</p>
            <p>When theſe thinges were ended, I ſaid:
<q rend="margQuotes">It will not be amiſſe that we recite the <hi>Letanies,</hi> if theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men shall thincke it fit.</q> 
               <hi>And I</hi> (ſaid the yong Lord) <hi>if you, and they be ſo contented, will be he, that shall recite them.</hi> They all made anſwere in the negatiue, ſaying to him;
<q rend="margQuotes">Your Lordshippe, would but weary your ſelfe, too <pb n="160" facs="tcp:2857:76"/>much.</q> 
               <hi>Nothing leſse,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but to me it will be, of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame contentment.</hi> And ſo, (w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> out more diſpute) they put the book into his hand; and (kneeling euen, by me, againſt a fourme) he began the <hi>Letanyes,</hi> to which we anſwearing,
<hi>Ora pro eo, Pray for him,</hi> there
<note n="(o)" place="margin">It muſt needes, be an obiect of great compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> was not a man amongſt vs, who accompanied not the words of his mouth with the tears of his eyes. And eſpecially, when with incredible af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and deuotion, he repeated, theſe wordes, <hi>A
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:2857:76"/>mala morte, A poreſtate diaboli, A poenis inferni, libera me Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Deliuer me, O Lord from an euill death, from the power of the diuell, and from the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of hell.</hi> But
<note n="(p)" place="margin">No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but only his ſins could moue him to teares.</note> he (O admirable repoſe of that mind) did not shead one teare. Nay my ſelfe being in teares, who held vp the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle by him (and not being able to repreſſe them) he ſtirred me with his elbow, and made other ſignes to them, that ſo, giuing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their weepinge, they might anſwere him. And <pb n="162" facs="tcp:2857:77"/>ſpeaking of it to me after ward, he ſaid,
<hi>That there wanted little, of their making him alſo weep, for company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Letanies</hi> were ended, he ſayd (turning to me)
<hi>Father, ſay you the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ouer me, that follow.</hi> And then, he tooke the light out of my hand, and ſo giuing me the booke, I ſaid thoſe praiers ouer him, which are wont to be ſaid, ouer ſuch as are in their laſt agony; <hi>Comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ao
<note n="(q)" place="margin">Theſe are as admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and affectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as any are vſed in the whol office of the holy Church; and I wish all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this, to procure to ſee &amp; reade them.</note> te omnipotenti deo &amp;c.</hi> And that other which followeth,
<hi>Deus miſericors, <pb n="163" facs="tcp:2857:77"/>Deus clemens &amp;c.</hi> And at the end of theſe, he ſayd with a loud voice, the <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> the <hi>Aue maria,</hi> the <hi>Credo,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Salue Regina;</hi> and ſo he returned to ſit downe, the others making the accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med circle about him. And ſo one, with repreſenting ſome ſentence of <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> another, ſome exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, another, ſome other ſpirituall Conſideration, we alwaies kept him aliue, and quicke, and euen all kindled in deuotion; till ſuch time, as the houre of <pb n="164" facs="tcp:2857:78"/>colebrating
<hi>Maſſe,</hi> approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</p>
            <p>Then the Noble Man ſayd thus: <hi>If theſe
<note n="(r)" place="margin">This rigour is vſed in thoſe partes, for the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencies which haue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metyms been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, in the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, by delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents.</note> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles be put vpon me to giue me payne, or punishment, let the will of my Prince be done, who is pleaſed to haue it ſo; but if the meaning be, but to make me ſure; in vaine is he tyed without, who is bound
<note n="(s)" place="margin">Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his hart was more chained, by the loue of God, then his handes could be, by a load of yron.</note> within.</hi> Vpon which wordes, all of vs being full
<note n="(t)" place="margin">They had great reaſon.</note> of tendernes; and in particuler one of thoſe <hi>Confortatori</hi> (who
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:2857:78"/>shewed himſelfe, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that whole night, as a moſt compaſſionate Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, in ſeruice of this Noble Man) cauſed the keyes to be inſtantly giuen him, and ſo tooke the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles off; which yet, the <hi>Baron</hi> would needs
<note n="(u)" place="margin">An humble, naturall, &amp; moſt Noble Soule.</note> kiſſe, and kiſſing them, he ſighed, and ſo held his peace.</p>
            <p>When he had been ſilent a while, and hauing made a ſigne that he deſired to confeſſe againe; and when he had bleſſed himſelfe, with the ſigne of the <hi>Croſſe; <pb n="166" facs="tcp:2857:79"/>Father</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">He is much ſolicued by the memory of his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Mother.</note>, (ſayd he) <hi>I who haue giuen ſo many diſguſtes, and ſo bitter ones, to my moſt deare Lady, &amp; Mother, through the whole courſe of my life; what comfort doth your Reuerence thinke, that I might be able to giue her in my death?</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">By dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wel (ſayd I) &amp; in a holy manner.</q> To which he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thus; <hi>How shall the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate woman come to know it?</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">I told him, that I would relate it to her by word of mouth; and in fine I would write it for her; and I will not only notify it (ſayd I) <pb n="167" facs="tcp:2857:79"/>to her, but to any other whome it may import to know it.</q> 
               <hi>It is inough,</hi> (ſayd he) &amp; he reached his hands out to me, that I might giue him one of myne, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, my word. And ſo he kiſſed it often, and holding it betweene both his, he continued to ſpeake after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I could wish, deare Father, that in my place, your Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence would often viſit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my Lady my Mother, after my death. And when ſo, you shal ſee her firſt, I deſire that you <pb n="168" facs="tcp:2857:80"/>will aske forgiuenes of her in my name, a thouſand, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand tymes, as heer I haue done, both now, and the other day, ſince I came to priſon. And eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, begge pardon of her, for ſuch, and ſuch a particuler offence, and then ſay to her thus;</hi> Your <hi>Troilus</hi> who is dead, begs that bleſſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your moſt afflicted Ladishippe, which being aliue, he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſerued, nor had time to aske. He further recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes the care of his ſoule to your Ladiship. He prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he beſeecheth, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iureth <pb n="169" facs="tcp:2857:80"/>your Ladiship, to graunt him this his laſt &amp; now only ſuite; that hauing put your ſoule in peace, you will not ſo much as reſent, or call to mind, and much leſſe procure to
<note n="(y)" place="margin">If ſhe thought that the aduerſe parties, whome he had wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, had proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with too much eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> reuenge your ſelfe, for any iniury; but that you will remit the whole, and your ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to the Eternall Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God.
<hi>Put her in mind, that it is the part of a</hi> Roman, <hi>and</hi> Chriſtian <hi>hart, after a generous manner to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don offences. And, giuing her all comfort, do you aſſure her, <pb n="170" facs="tcp:2857:81"/>that I haue particulerly re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſed, all thoſe irreuerent wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that I haue formerly vſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes her; and that I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> remembred all thoſe moſt ſweet, deare benefits, which I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> receaued from her; and all thoſe Maternall fauours, which she hath vouchſafed me. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, let her know, the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable contentment that I haue to thincke of the
<note n="(z)" place="margin">This was a Mother, not only of her ſonnes body, but of his ſoule alſo.</note> Chriſtian loue, which she hath expreſſed to me, in this laſt paſſage; without euer reflecting vpon thoſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and great demerits of myne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say to her moreouer, that <pb n="171" facs="tcp:2857:81"/>I dye her ſonne, &amp; a ſonne, who is moſt profoundly penitent, for all the ill wordes, and deeds that I haue euer vttered, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed againſt her; and that, in the other world, I will by Gods grace, be as gratefull to her, as I haue beene vngratefull, heer. Relate to her my laſt paſſage, in moſt particuler manner; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige her, liberally to reward al my followers, who haue been in priſon, vpon my occaſion. Of whome, I doe with all the very bowells of my hart, aske pardon, for the payne, and perill, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into I did idly, and abſurdly caſt <pb n="172" facs="tcp:2857:82"/>them. And aſſure her, in a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that if for nothing els, yet eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for the very diſguſtes which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue giuen to her, I shall dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> content; finding a kind of ioy in my hart, that I performe this pennance, in this manner, which I haue ſo well deſerued. And ſo, I dying in ſuch ſort, a your Reuerence may be pleaſed to let her know, she cannot but receaue ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in my death; and she will alſo find, that she is euen engaged, ſo to range her ſelfe to the will of God, as, by his mercy, I haue done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To my Lady, my Grand-Mother, <pb n="173" facs="tcp:2857:82"/>what shall I ſay, deere Father? O how compaſſiue am I of her great age! VVhat paine doth my ſoule feele, for that paine of hers! Giue her alſo to vnderſtand, that I begge pardon of her, for ſo many diſguſtes, as, in this old age of hers, I haue giuen her; beſeeching her in my name, that as long as she shall liue, she will weekly, cauſe a Maſſe to be celebrated, for my ſoule. And in like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly aske pardon of my Lord Marqueſſe, my Vncle, from the moſt inward parts of my ſoule, as I alſo doe of the reſt of my
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:2857:83"/>bloud; beſeeching them all to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cuſe this youth, or rather ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance of myne. Putting alſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in mind, that once we shal al me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in heauen. And if euer your R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerence can procure to be in my Caſtles, aske pardon, I beſeech you, in my name, a hundred tymes, of all my vaſſalls. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a promiſe to them, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of the ill example which
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue giuen them, I will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get them in heauen, when by the mercy of God, I shall be there; and let them, in the meane tyme, excuſe my youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forget not alſo to do this <pb n="175" facs="tcp:2857:83"/>office, with</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">This was a perſon of great authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and place, who took his exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> Monſig<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. the Gouernour of Rome,
<hi>who about ſome foure tymes, hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined me, with ſo much reſpect and courteſy. Giuing him aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, from me, that although my death do grieue me, yet I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept willingly thereof. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching him, that, when tyme shall ſerue, he wil alſo
<note n="(b)" place="margin">vvith how great pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, he ſpeakes of the Pope, as he was his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Paſtour, &amp; with obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance as of his Prince.</note> aſſure</hi> our Lord, Pope Clement, his Holynes,
<hi>that I dye his moſt deuoted Sonne; and moſt ſatisfyed, with the proceeding of his</hi> Holynes, <hi>towardes me. VVith this moreouer, that am grieued at the very rootes of <pb n="176" facs="tcp:2857:84"/>my
<note n="(c)" place="margin">A noble circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ciuility and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy.</note> hart, for hauing ginen</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Holynes, <hi>ſo much cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> trouble, and griefe; eſpecially <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this beginning of his</hi> Pontif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate,
<hi>and in the middest of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ioy, which hath beene expreſſed for his aſſumption, to the</hi> Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtolique. <hi>And let him b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> further told, that by placing my ſelfe, as I doe at your feet,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make accoumpt, that I lay my head vnder the feet of his</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes; <hi>that ſo he may vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to giue me his benediction. I hauing this comfort, in the midſt of all my afflictions, that his ſentence, and my death, will <pb n="177" facs="tcp:2857:84"/>ſerue to his whole State, for a lawfull, and plentifull example of his Iustice. And verily, if it grieue me, at this tyme, to dye, it doth alſo grieue me, that euen by my death, I am not able to giue complete ſat is faction, to his</hi> Holynes. <hi>For
<note n="(d)" place="margin">what a noble ciuill Soule was this?</note> as much as he, being my Father, and my Paſtour, he cannot, in fine, but feele the death of a Sonne, and sheep, of his, with diſpleaſure, and griefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon which wordes, he finding, (euen more then before) that there fell ſome teares from mine eyes, to <pb n="178" facs="tcp:2857:85"/>his handes, <hi>This is well in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed,</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>your</hi> Reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence, <hi>commendes my courage, but why then do you weepe your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? At least, let not others ſee you.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Then I replying ſaid. Do you belieue, my Sonne, that I haue no fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in me? Do you thinke perhaps, that I am ſome piece of marble? Proceed you on to the reſt.</q> And then, naming diuers of his particuler friendes, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired me to aske pardon for him, of them all; and this he did, with wordes of <pb n="179" facs="tcp:2857:85"/>extreame ſweetenes, and prudence. This being then ſaid by him with a moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably intrepide hart, he concluded with this deſire; <hi>I beſeech your</hi> Reuerence, <hi>that in the laſt place, you will begge pardon for me, of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, as I my ſelfe do now, with the moſt internall part of my hart; and of your ſelfe, I aske my</hi> Pennance, <hi>and</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</p>
            <p>Which as ſoone as I had giuen him, the Brothers of that
<hi>Congregation</hi> of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia,</hi> did put vs in mind
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:2857:86"/>how it was tyme that <hi>Maſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> should be celebrated; and ſo the Prieſt, as ſoone as he was veſted, began. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout yong Lord, &amp; I knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling togeather againſt a four me, he ſayd thus to me. <hi>The Prieſt is beginning</hi> Maſſe; <hi>&amp; I (with your good leaue) wil haue a new</hi> Reconcilation, <hi>according to that, which my Good Angell shall bring to my remembrance, of whome I haue deſired this fauour.</hi> The
<hi>Prieſt</hi> was ſaying the <hi>Confiteor</hi> at the foote of the
<hi>Altar;</hi> to whome one of the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:2857:86"/>(making anſwere) was ſo ouer wrought with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, that he could not get to the end of it; in ſuch ſort, as that it was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that ſome other should doe it for him. Then the good Noble Man, who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ſoftly to the <hi>Coſiteor,</hi> leaning towardes me, ſayd thus, <hi>Giue
<note n="(e)" place="margin">He had the guift of teares, in a ſtrange meaſure.</note> me leaue to weep, whyleſt I ſay the</hi> Confiteor, <hi>ſince that Gentleman weepes ſo bitterly, to whoſe office it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not greatly, that he should weep.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">I anſwered, that he might weep in the name of <pb n="182" facs="tcp:2857:87"/>God; ſince he had giue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him ſo great deſire ſo to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q> And it was an admirable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of diuine grace, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, I ſaw the tears ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe his cheekes, and powring themſelues, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon the cushion, that lay before him.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Confiteor</hi> was done, and all
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Till after the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</note> the whyle that the <hi>Prieſt</hi> was reading with a loud voice, he did not mooue at all, but was moſt fixedly attentiue, and as it were rapt towards the
<note n="(g)" place="margin">The <hi>Crucifixe</hi> was of ſtone, or wood, but his mind was v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Original and not vpon the picture, which was but a picture or Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge.</note> 
               <hi>Crucifixe,</hi> vpon the
<hi>Altar,</hi> 
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:2857:87"/>which was there moſt deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utly made. And shortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, turning towards myne eare, he accuſed himſelfe of diuers little thinges, which ſuddenly then did ſurprize his mind. And the
<hi>Prieſt</hi> being come to
<note n="(h)" place="margin">A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle of Maſſe.</note>
               <hi>Surſum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da; Father</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>do you thinke indeed, that by ſuch a death as this, and ſo well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I may yet go ſtraight to heauen?</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">And why not (ſayd I) with ſo great and ſo well conditioned affectuouſnes of mind, might your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship vndergo this death, as <pb n="184" facs="tcp:2857:88"/>that your ſoule would be ſure to flye vp inſtantly, from the blocke, into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</q> 
               <hi>O my God!</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>And what kind of affectuouſnes muſt that be! O teach it me a little! O that our Lord, would graunt it to me!</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Pray (ſayd I) very earneſtly vnto him for it, and peraduenture he will graunt it.</q> At which tyme, the
<hi>Prieſt</hi> being in the very act of the <hi>Eleuation of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Lord,</hi> the yong No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Man, ſpake theſe very, very wordes. <hi>O bone Ieſu, ſis mihi, in hac hora, Ieſus. O deare <pb n="185" facs="tcp:2857:88"/>Lord Ieſus, be thou, in this houre, a Ieſus to me.</hi> And this he ſayd, with ſo ardent affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of mind, though with a low voice, as that after it, he was wholy immoueable, till the <hi>Prieſt</hi> went on, to
<note n="(i)" place="margin">The later end of Maſſe.</note>
               <hi>Domine non ſum dignus, &amp;c.</hi> And then, he ſayd thus to me. <hi>I haue not, Father, beene attentiue, either when the</hi> Pater Noſter, <hi>or the</hi> Agnus Dei, <hi>was ſayd; may I yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe communicate?</hi> I anſwered, that for the preſent, he should do ſuch a
<note n="(k)" place="margin">This was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his breaſt, or ſome ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, which might be done at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, whileſt I was giuing <pb n="186" facs="tcp:2857:89"/>him
<hi>Abſolution.</hi> Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, he went, of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to the
<hi>Altar;</hi> and kneeling downe, did with exemplar deuotion, receaue the
<hi>most Bleſsed Sacrament;</hi> &amp; ſoone after, he came backe from
<hi>Maſſe,</hi> towardes me, where he remained, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any motion at all.</p>
            <p>After this, turning about to all them who did aſſiſt, he ſaid, <hi>I giue thankes to you all, for your Charity and courteſy; and pardon, I beſeech you, the painfull night, which I haue brought vpon you.</hi> And <pb n="187" facs="tcp:2857:89"/>then, he deſired me, for the loue of him, to repeate thoſe wordes, to euery one of them, in particuler; and ſo I did. Being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intreated to ſit downe, the wonted circle was made about him. Where euery one procured, to animate him, towardes that combat which was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at hand; by repreſenting the shortnes of the paine, the imme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſity of the reward, the vanity of the world; &amp; aboue all, the aboundant grace, which, in the ſpace of ſo few houres, our Lord <pb n="188" facs="tcp:2857:90"/>had communicated to his ſoule; and had giuen him with all, ſuch a pregnant ſigne of his <hi>Predeſtination;</hi> wherein the Noble Youth, did
<note n="(l)" place="margin">And ſo he might moſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly doe.</note> shew to find extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary guſt.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the many diſoourſes which were made to this purpoſe, as wel by the <hi>Confortatori,</hi> as by our Fathers, I vſed this.
<q rend="margQuotes">And what thinke you, <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> will the grace which God hath giuen you, be ſufficient to make you beare this punishment? Nay I tell <pb n="189" facs="tcp:2857:90"/>you, that in imitation of Chriſt, you should do well to deſire it, and that deſire, would ſerue to make it, a ſmall matter, to you. Nay it would make it ſeeme no punishment at all; &amp; laſtly it would make it ſeeme ſweet. Euen as it hapned to Chriſt our Lord himſelfe, to
<note n="(m)" place="margin">The immenſe loue which our lord Ieſus bare to man, made all that he ſuffered, ſeeme little to him.</note> whom his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> ſeemed ſo ſmall a matter, that whereas others called it, by the name of a huge thing, an <hi>Ocean,</hi> a deep ſea,
<hi>(Veni in altitudinem maris, &amp; tempeſtas demerſit me)</hi> himſelf
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:2857:91"/> doth call it, but a Cupfull, <hi>(Calicem quem dedit mihi pater, non vis vt biba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illum?)</hi> Againe, after that huge heape of bitternes, and tormentes which he had endured, it ſeemed nothing to him. For being asked by thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples who were going to <hi>Emaus,</hi> if he knew of that vaſt cruelty, which had lately then, bin executed at
<hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> vpon the perſon of the greateſt Saint of God; he anſweared, by asking, <hi>Quae?</hi> for in fine he eſteemed it all as nothing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <pb n="191" facs="tcp:2857:91"/>ſpeaking of his
<hi>Paſſion,</hi> he vſed the word <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> ſaying,
<hi>Baptiſmo habeo bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizari, et quomodo coarctor</hi> &amp;c. And you know that <hi>bathes</hi> do ſerue for delicacy. What ſay you then <hi>Signor Troilo?</hi> Doth not your punishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by this time, ſeeme ſmall to you?</q> 
               <hi>Small;</hi> (ſaith he?) <hi>it ſeemeth nothing. Yet can I not ſay, either that it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or yet very pleaſant; but yet neuertheleſſe, it is deare to me, and as ſuch I prize it. And
<note n="(n)" place="margin">How mightily this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, grew vp in grace, euen by mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> I do aſſure you, that at the preſent, it would be as it <pb n="192" facs="tcp:2857:92"/>were, a kind of trouble for me, to eſcape it. Before I deſired to eſcape; I ſighed for it; I laboured for it; and I know not what of that kind. But I had not then, that knowledg of my ſelfe, which now, by the fauour of God, me thinkes I haue; in ſuch ſort, that now, I can affirme to you, in the worde of Truth, that I
<note n="(o)" place="margin">This ſo ardent deſire, of ſuffering for his ſinnes, muſt needs be a great diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for them, through the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſt our Lord.</note> deſire my end, how painfull ſoeuer it may be, towardes the remiſſion of my ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this, another Father ſaid;
<q rend="margQuotes">Your Lordship ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth wiſely; for in fine, God knoweth, whether other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <pb n="193" facs="tcp:2857:92"/>you should euer haue beene ſo well prepared for death.</q> Whereupon, one of the
<hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nfortatori</hi> proceeded, ſaying:
<q rend="margQuotes">If your Lordship had dyed naturally in your bed; what, with the paine of your body, and the anguish of your mind; it may be you would ſcarce haue beene maiſter of your ſelfe. And if you had dyed, by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accident, perhaps you would not haue had time, to bring forth, ſo much as the name of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> Whereas now, it
<note n="(p)" place="margin">Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing firſt, the grace of God, as is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward.</note> is in a manner, <pb n="194" facs="tcp:2857:93"/> in your owne power, to dye as well as you will, your ſelfe; with what greife of your ſinnes you will; with what loue of chriſt you will; and, in a word, in that beſt manner, which the grace of Almighty God will impart to you; which we perceaue, euen ſo to ouerflow your ſoule, that we are as much aſtonished, as comforted, by the knowledge therof.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Heereunto the conſtant Noble Man, made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. <hi>You shall know, that by the goodnes of God, I find not in <pb n="195" facs="tcp:2857:93"/>my ſelfe, any trouble, or tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and me
<note n="(q)" place="margin">No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the very hand of God, was able ſo to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted him, through theſe ſtony wayes. And it ſeemes, that God commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cated himſelfe to the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, in a very particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> thinks I am in a hand which beares me vp. I deſire, and I reſolue to dye, in that manner, which I shall be taught to be the beſt; and I am moſt ready, to obey in all that, which for the ſauing of my ſoule shall be commanded me.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">This, ſaid I, you shal therfore do. You shal barre you ſelfe, in that houre, of ſome eaſe. That is, you shal for the loue of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of what he did and ſuffered for you, depriue your ſelfe of ſomewhat, <pb n="196" facs="tcp:2857:94"/> which you might haue; and which, at that time, might be agreeable to you. For, if you doe well remember it, they gaue twice, vnto our Lord, to drinke. The firſt time, when they gaue him <hi>vinagre,</hi> he drunke; but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they gaue him wine, as ſoon as he had taſted it, he put it by. But do you know the reaſon? It was this. To ſuch as were condemned to dye, it was the cuſtome to giue wine, with an infuſion of <hi>myrrhe;</hi> that by the comfort thereof, they might faint <pb n="197" facs="tcp:2857:94"/>the leſſe, vnder their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Now our Lord (who was pleaſed to depriue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe entierly, and fully, of all conſolation, for loue of vs, and for our example) refuſed that, but he accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the <hi>vinagre,</hi>
               </q> which was mingled with
<note n="(r)" place="margin">With Gall.</note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt bitter ingredient;
<q>that ſo, he might ſuffer the moſt he could; both for our example, and benefit other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Proueditore</hi> ſayd, that this was moſt certainly true; whereupon ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound <pb n="198" facs="tcp:2857:95"/>thoſe wordes, which Chriſt ſpake vpon the <hi>croſſe, Deus Deus meus, vt quid dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquiſti me?</hi> That Chriſt our Lord, did greiue thereat, becauſe the <hi>Diuinity,</hi> began as it were, to hide it ſelfe from the <hi>Humanity;</hi> &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently by little &amp; little, his life was leauing him; &amp; by occaſion thereof, he was able to ſuffer no longer; which the moſt enamoured Ieſus obſeruing, did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of the matter, to his <hi>Father,</hi> by the wordes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="199" facs="tcp:2857:95"/>
            <p>To theſe thinges a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ours, adding other deuout, and short diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the <hi>Confortatore</hi> ſayd;
<q rend="margQuotes">That for the tyme his ſoule was ſufficiently fed; &amp; that it would be well done, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh his body.</q> The Baron anſwered, <hi>that there was no neede.</hi> But they preſſing it much, there was brought in ſome wine, by a ſeruant of the Lord
<note n="(s)" place="margin">This Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement, is the place of greateſt confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce which the Pope beſtowes</note> 
               <hi>Gouernour</hi> of the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> which, one of the Gentlemen there preſent, powring forth into a glaſſe, preſented to the <hi>Baron;</hi> who
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:2857:96"/>ſayd again, that it was who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly needles. <hi>And yet</hi> (ſayd he, turning then towardes me) <hi>if I should need it, your
<note n="(t)" place="margin">A good memory he had, and a more pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence told me a whyle agoe, that in imitation of Chriſt, I should doe well to depriue my ſelfe thereof. Father, is it not ſo?</hi> Neuertheles, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by al the Aſſiſtants, that he would drinke, or at leaſt, that he would, ſo much, as wash his mouth; this laſt he did twice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſwallowing any wine at all. And this was ſo much more remarkeable, becauſe <pb n="201" facs="tcp:2857:96"/>ſuch as are in that caſe, vſe to be extremely taken with thirſt, and it is wont to be held, for one of their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt torments.</p>
            <p>The wine being then carryed away, diuers que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions were asked of this moſt Illuſtrious Lord, to which he
<note n="(u)" place="margin">Note &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at theſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweares, which are ſo ful of piety. wiſedom and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</note> anſwered, with ſo great prudence &amp; iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, that more could not be imagined. He was asked firſt (for, of many, I will mention only a few) &amp; this firſt queſtion he was asked often;) <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi>
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:2857:97"/>will your Lordship haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing? He ſtill anſwered;
<hi>that he deſired nothing,</hi> ſauing that once, he held his peace, but made a ſigne vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Beſides, he was often asked, <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> of what are you thinking? Someti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes he a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered, <hi>vpon nothing in particuler;</hi> Sometimes, <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our Lord;</hi> Sometimes,
<hi>vpon my ſinnes;</hi> Sometimes; <hi>vpon my approaching end;</hi> Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, he ſayd, <hi>I thinke vpon the ſo many guiftes, which God hath beſtowed vpon me, &amp; that I haue been, ſo very vngrateful;
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:2857:97"/>yea &amp; euen vnmindfull of them all.</hi> Being then asked in this manner,
<q rend="margQuotes">Doth your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship dye willingly?</q> He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thus: <hi>And what? would you haue me buſtle against the order of the Prince? Or should I not be content, with the prouidence, and good pleaſure of God?</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Is it poſſible, ſay done, that the Diuell should not ſtriue, to make you thinke your death vniuſt?</q> 
               <hi>I do not,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>eſteeme it only to be iuſt; but moſt iuſt; and as for the Diuell, I neither haue, nor wil I haue, any more to do with him,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:2857:98"/>I haue had inough, and too much of him already.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Another asked him what he ſayd, of the Lady his Mother, his Friendes, his Kinred, and himſelfe; if he were not much afflicted, with the thought thereof?</q> 
               <hi>Concerning my Lady, my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>I confeſſe, that in the moſt inward partes of my hart, I find extreme affliction; but, on the other ſide, I reioyce that I am paying the offences, that I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt her, with my bloud. And I hope, that the readines wherewith I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace <pb n="205" facs="tcp:2857:98"/>this pennance, for my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked carriage towards her, will be ſo well accepted by Almighty God; that he may, through his goodnes, giue her no ſmall comfort, euen by this very death of myne. I thinke vpon my kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with grief, as hauing been a cauſe of payne, and trouble to them. Of my friends, as hauing giuen them ill example. Of my ſelfe, I take no care; for behold who
<note n="(x)" place="margin">A great fayth, &amp; hope, &amp; loue.</note> doth it for me;</hi> making a ſigne towards the
<hi>Crucifixe,</hi> which he had hard by him.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Being asked, whether the tyme did ſeeme long to <pb n="206" facs="tcp:2857:99"/>him or short?</q> 
               <hi>Neither
<note n="(y)" place="margin">This doe I find to be a ſtrange anſwere, in the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laciue degree of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes.</note> long</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>nor short.</hi> And another replying to him thus; Is it poſſible, that you are not grieued, that you muſt dye? <hi>I do not</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>deny, but that I am grieued at it; but yet it neither troubles me, nor ſomuch as alters me, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſee.</hi> It being wished, that he should ſuffer his chaire, to be drawn a litle forward, that ſo he might ſit at grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eaſe; <hi>To what end</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>should I giue my body eaſe? I am well heere; and with the help of God, I shall be shortly
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:2857:99"/>free, from needing that, or any thing els.</hi> Being deſired to raiſe, and reſt his feet, vpon a place of aduantage, where they vſed to kneele, for that ſo, he should be in a more commodious poſture; he ſayd (drawing neer towards myne eare,) <hi>Father, it is a piece of ill manners, to fit with a mans legs raiſed vp, in the preſence of other men.</hi> But I telling him no, and aduiſing him how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, that he would ſet them vp; he did inſtantly accommodate himſelfe to my deſire.
<q rend="margQuotes">Being asked, to <pb n="208" facs="tcp:2857:100"/> what deuotions, he had bin moſt particulerly affected:</q> He anſweared,
<hi>To that of our
<note n="(z)" place="margin">He was euer much deuoted to our B. Lady.</note> Bleſſed Lady, in whoſe honour, I did dayly recite her Office, but with an impure mouth; and how then, could that be accepted by her? And till within theſe two yeares, I made</hi> ſaid he, <hi>much account of going to Confeſſion, which through the mercy of my Lord, I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued neuer to intermitt, vnleſſe it were by ſome very vnlucky accident, that should haue inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it ſelfe. And I euer carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed liuing, in my hart, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory <pb n="209" facs="tcp:2857:100"/>of manie thinges, which formerly, vpon ſeuerall occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had beene repreſented to me by ſundry Religious Fathers, with whome I had much conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> (inſinuating therby, as I conceaue, the Fathers of the <hi>Chieſa Nuoua.) And when I had meanes, to do it in priuate, I neuer failed any day, to ſalute the Bleſſed Virgin vpon my bare knees.</hi> And then, I ſaying (I know not well, vpon what occaſion) <hi>Ah poore Signor Troilo. Poore</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>I was, when I was without the grace of my Lord God, but now, I take <pb n="210" facs="tcp:2857:101"/>my ſelfe to be rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then the tyme of his end drawing on apace, we riſing vp from our ſeats, did circle him in, vpon our knees. And (after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of two Quires, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably anſwering one another) we began the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<hi>Penitentiall Pſalms;</hi> pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſome of the verſes now and then, and cauſing him, to reſume diuers of them. They being ended, he was aduiſed to ſay often, <hi>Eia
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Theſe are parts of ſome
<hi>Hymnes,</hi> which are reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the holy Church, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our lord Ieſus, &amp; our B. Lady.</note> ergo aduocata noſtra &amp;c.</hi> And then, <hi>Maria mater <pb n="211" facs="tcp:2857:101"/>gratiae.</hi> And then againe,
<hi>Recordare Ieſu pie,</hi> and the like. Which he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, with ſo cleare a voyce, ſo conſtant a memory, and with a countenance ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene, that all ſuch as were preſent (himſelfe only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) did weep outright. Which he obſeruing, and making ſilence, and taking his own face into his hands, he ſtood ſtill a whyle, in mentall prayer. And then turning towardes me, he ſayd; <hi>Confiteor
<note n="(b)" place="margin">The entrance whereby, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to makour <hi>Confiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note> Deo Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potenti, &amp; tibi Pater. I accuſe <pb n="212" facs="tcp:2857:102"/>my ſelfe of this, and this, and that; Ideo
<note n="(c)" place="margin">This we vſe to ſay when we haue ended it.</note> precor &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then, inſtantly he added this: <hi>Father, I would deſire
<note n="(d)" place="margin">A far greater matter it was to aske this ſuite, then to grant it.</note> this laſt fauour of you; that you would confeſſe me at the blocke; and that, whyleſt I, on the one ſide, with my beades in my hand, might ſay,</hi> O bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Ieſu, ſis mihi Ieſus; O good Lord Ieſus, be thou a Ieſus to me; <hi>and you on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Ego te abſoluo &amp;c. I abſolue thee &amp;c. <hi>at the ſame inſtant, the iron might fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my necke.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Not ſo, my Lord, ſayd I. For ſo, by
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:2857:102"/>giuing a ſigne to the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner for the cuttinge off your head, I should becom
<note n="(e)" place="margin">By the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> of the holy Church, a Prieſt may not cooperat to the death of any man though neuer ſo far off; but only for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents in courſe of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce; nor then nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but with particuler diſpenſation, and that in very rare caſes. The <hi>Inquifition</hi> hath nothing to do heerin, but only examineth, and leaueth ſuch as are faulty and impenitent to the ſecular Iudges.</note> 
                  <hi>Irregular.</hi> No, no, I will not doe it, by any meanes. But then, obſeruing that he was much afflicted, by my negatiue, and ſo rather to quiet him, then for any thing elſe, I ſayd it might perhappes be thus, better done. You may <hi>confeſſe</hi> at the blocke; and being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, you may begin to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke <pb n="214" facs="tcp:2857:103"/> the name of <hi>Ieſus;</hi> and when I shall ſee, that the Executioner is ready to let downe the iron, I may ſay with a lowd voice, <hi>Ego te ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluo &amp;c.</hi> Yet perhapps a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, this would be more inconuenient; for by giuing you a ſigne, of when the iron were vpon the point of falling, it might fright you in ſuch ſort, as that, if by the motion of your body, it should not fall iuſt vpon you, it would mangle you, and ſo afflict you, with a double paine, and a double <pb n="215" facs="tcp:2857:103"/>death. I will not do it, by any meanes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At theſe words, caſting his head vpon my boſome, he ſayd;
<hi>Ah Father, euen by all that loue which you beare to this miſerable ſinnefull ſoule, do me this fauour. I make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to you, in the name, and by the help of God, that you shal not put me into terrour by it. For Gods loue belieue me; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you giue me credit.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon yet, I continuing, as I had reſolued before; <hi>O God</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>and might not thy diuine Maiesty, mooue the hart <pb n="216" facs="tcp:2857:104"/>of this my Father, to eſteeme me worthy of this fauour?</hi> Well, be of courage (ſayd I, to quiet him) I promiſe you, that I will do it. <hi>Then giue me</hi> (anſwered he) <hi>that
<note n="(f)" place="margin">The handes of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Prieſts, are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated with great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity.</note> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred hand of yours.</hi> And I gaue it to him, with this purpoſe, that if he should not remember it at the blocke, as I verily thought that he would not, then I would let it paſſe; and that if he remembred it, and did franckly call for it, I would performe it. But it ſeemed (as I ſaid) to me, that a man
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:2857:104"/>could hardly be of ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted a mind; as that, in ſo hard a paſſage, his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory would ſerue him for ſuch a buſines; and that, wheras all men procure to diuert their mind fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a blow, this
<hi>Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> would needs haue an expreſſe ſigne ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But, in fine, where the grace of God doth enter, it produceth effects, which do farre out-ſtripp all the power of nature; and no wit of man arriueth to them.</p>
            <p>When I had made him this promiſe; <hi>I
<note n="(g)" place="margin">His hart wrought mightily towards humility</note> would know</hi> 
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:2857:105"/>(ſaid he) <hi>whether your</hi> Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>will not thincke it fit, that I giue thankes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand pardon, of them who haue had moſt to do with me, in this place.</hi> I told him, that I liked well of it; and hauing giuen him
<hi>Abſolution,</hi> I intreated him by a ſigne, to ſit downe. Then he ſaid; <hi>Father, take you the care of my iourney from hence to the blocke, as you haue already promiſed; and you shall go aduertiſing me, from pace to pace, of ſuch thinges as are fit, that I may haue, my whole ſoule</hi>
               <hi>for God alone.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">I will aduertiſe <pb n="219" facs="tcp:2857:105"/>you, (ſaid I) of all; Keep your ſelfe prepared, and ſit downe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoone as he was ſet, all the ſtringes of our very harts, ſeemed to be moued at once, to pray him that he would be mindfull of vs in heauen. And
<note n="(h)" place="margin">It is a ſigne that they ſaw ſtrange tokens of Gods fauour in him.</note> euery one of vs who were preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, both with wordes, and tears, did reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend himſelfe to him, the beſt he could; and we were not able to ſatisfie our ſelues, in the deſire we had of expreſſing kindnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him. And verily,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:2857:106"/>this was a death, of ſo much tendernes, that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of it at this time, doth affect me, at the very ſoule. Only the yong Noble Man, remained with a moſt Angelicall Countenance; and with a hart which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not ſo much as to know, what belonged to feare.</p>
            <p>This
<note n="(i)" place="margin">A deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of <hi>Signor Troilo's</hi> perſon, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion.</note> 
               <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> was tal of ſtature; of delicate conſtitution; of colour ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oliuaſter, then very faire; of black haire &amp; thick; of face, neither fatte, nor
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:2857:106"/>leane; his eyes were blacke, and full, and quicke; his noſe ſweetely raiſed; his mouth of a iuſt proportion, &amp; rather ſmiling, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other wiſe; his forhead compete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpatious, &amp; he had not ſo much as one ſingle haire vpon his cheekes. Of a ſweete voice, of ready an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweares; &amp; ſo complete in good fashion, that euen at the block, he failed not to ſalute, &amp; reſalute all men, according to the occaſion, &amp; their condition; and not being able to take of his hat
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:2857:107"/>himſelfe, to make others do it for him. It hapned once that I deſired him to let me wipe his face with a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hercheife; not that he was in any ſweate, but only to refresh him a little. But he, hauing ſuffered me, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to do him that ſeruice, ſayd; <hi>Father, I need not this.</hi> But I deſired, that at leaſt he would rub his face with his own hands, for it would refresh him; and inſtantly doing ſo, he ſaid, to me in myne eare; <hi>Father, I had an extreame deſire, to ſtretch
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:2857:107"/>my ſelfe, but me thought, it had ſomewhat of the Clowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In concluſion, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all thoſe ſouldiars who had kept guard ouer him, to paſſe before him, one, by one; and ſo,
<note n="(k)" place="margin">It is a true ſigne, &amp; a certain fruite of true pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a mans ſelfe mightily for Gods ſake.</note> caſting himſelfe vpon his knees, to euery one of them, as they ſingly paſſed, he asked pardon, moſt humbly of them, with Noble and Chriſtian wordes; and he left them alſo, liberall donatiues. To the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Porter,</hi> he did the like, and more; excuſing himſelf
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:2857:108"/>for the trouble which he had giuen him.</p>
            <p>But now there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned no more to be done, for the time was run out, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<note n="(l)" place="margin">In thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes there ringeth a bell eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, noone, &amp; night, when all men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite 3. ſhort prayers, in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Incarnation of Chriſt our Lord. This they do whereſoeuer they be, when the bell ringes, though it be in the ſtreets; and there they ſalute one another, with a wiſh of the good day, or night.</note> 
               <hi>Aue Maria</hi> bell, did ſound. Vpon the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whereof, we al recited that prayer, and he ſaid it alſo, vpon his knees. Then ſaluting all the company, he ſate down, &amp; was ſilent. And whileſt he held his peace, we ſpake amongſt <pb n="225" facs="tcp:2857:108"/>our ſelues, with aſtonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at many things, which we had obſerued in him, &amp; they were theſe. He did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſweate. He neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned of any thing. He neuer placed himſelfe, with any shew of wearines vpon his chaire He neuer shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any vnquietnes. He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wept, but whyleſt he was making his confeſſion. He neuer ſought to eaſe himſelfe, in the courſe of Nature. He neuer had any thirſt. He neuer fainted. He was neuer ſleepy. He
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:2857:109"/>was neuer ouerwroght with ſorrow. He was euer fresh, and ſtrong, hauing been, in that night, ſo many, and many tymes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his knees. He euer anſwered readily, and with a liuely voice. His memory neuer failed, or ſo much as wauered. He was handſomely, and modeſtly apparelled. He
<note n="(m)" place="margin">A ſtrange image of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, was this yonge Noble Man.</note> ſpake not ſo much as an inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate word. He neuer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed a deſire of any thing. He had, at certayne tymes, and vpon certaine occaſions, a diſcharged, and <pb n="227" facs="tcp:2857:109"/>ſmiling countenance. He did completely giue euery man thoſe titles of reſpect, which was his due; without fayling ſo much as once; as to one, of
<hi>Reuerence,</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, of <hi>Honour;</hi> to another of
<hi>You.</hi> He declared, moſt currantly, his laſt <hi>VVill,</hi> which was, a sheet of paper, long. He was not taken by paſſionate tendernes, but only vpon the ſpeach of the Lady his Mother. He ſpake moſt honourably, &amp; chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly, of the Prince, &amp; of the Iudges; yea and euen of
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:2857:110"/>them, who proſecuted the cauſe againſt him. All which particulers, or the moſt part of them, do hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen otherwiſe, in others, who are ſubiect to the like condition. So that all thoſe old experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced <hi>Confortatori</hi> of that <hi>Congregation,</hi> which is called of the <hi>Miſericordia,</hi> were amazed, to ſee how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly the Grace of God, had wrought vpon that ſoule, in the ſpace of a few houres.</p>
            <p>When this moſt deuout Noble Man, had thus held
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:2857:110"/>his peace, and we had been diſcourſing, amongſt our ſelues, of the thinges afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, he calling me towards him, who yet was ſtanding not farre off, ſpake to me, in this manner. <hi>Deare Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let vs make our laſt Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God.</hi> And then he made a short recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, of all his faults; and began
<note n="(n)" place="margin">A happy ſoule to be ſo ſpeedily, and ſo intierly cleanſed.</note> to accuſe himſelf, of thinges ſo extreamely ſmall; as hath giuen occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; matter to this ſoule of myne, vntill this day, wherein I write, and will, <pb n="230" facs="tcp:2857:111"/>vntil the houre of my death, both to be comforted, and confounded.</p>
            <p>Being vpon the end of his Confeſſion, he fell into a moſt ardent weeping; in ſuch ſort, as that bowing downe his head towards my hand, I was not able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the heat of his breath. And when I ſayd to him,
<q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Troylo</hi> my Sonne; Caſt a bridle vpon thoſe teares of yours; doe not exaſperate your own wound; it is now inough, and againe inough; you haue wept inough; you <pb n="231" facs="tcp:2857:111"/>will haue tyme to weep yet againe, when you come to lay your Head vpon the blocke, for
<note n="(o)" place="margin">He was to ſuffer death for his miſdeds, but he was to beare it patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the loue of Chriſt</note> Chriſt.</q> His anſwere was this; <hi>I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready told you Father, and now I tell you ſo once againe; I weep for my ſinnes, and not for my death. And when your</hi> Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>shall haue giuen me</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, <hi>and I shall haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the</hi> Pennance, <hi>which you will impoſe (which only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues to be accompanyed with tears) you shall find, that I will weep no more.</hi> And iuſt ſo it hapned; for wiping his face <pb n="232" facs="tcp:2857:112"/>when I had <hi>abſolued</hi> him, &amp; I hauing acquainted him, with ſome neceſſityes of myne owne, to the end that he might giue me
<note n="(p)" place="margin">By this holy prayers in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</note> aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, in the ſight of our Lord; he remayned, with eyes as full of ſerenity, and as voyd of teares, as if, in all his life, he had neuer wept.</p>
            <p>But then hauing raiſed himſelfe, it was thought fit, by all the Company, that certaine <hi>Pſalmes</hi> should be repeated, whereof, I was to po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der ſome of the verſes, <pb n="233" facs="tcp:2857:112"/>togeather with the
<hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatori;</hi> till ſuch time, as his houre should ariue. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſayd, <hi>It is now broade day, and there cannot be much time remayning. Our
<note n="(q)" place="margin">Great piety &amp; gratitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</note> Lord be bleſsed, for making me paſſe through this night, ſo happily, and ſo holily. I thanke you deare Father, &amp; you Gentlemen, for your ſo greate fauour. The good God reward you for it.</hi> And heere, all of vs recommending our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues againe to his prayers, we alſo againe beganne the Pſalmes.</p>
            <pb n="234" facs="tcp:2857:113"/>
            <p>At this time, the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner</hi> came in, and no man had the hart to tell him of it; but he perceiuing that there was a preſſe of people, did gently turne his face about, and ſaw him, As ſoone as he had ſet eye vpon him, he was not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with it at all; but
<note n="(r)" place="margin">Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted, holy courage.</note> he armed himſelfe only with the ſigne of the <hi>Holy Croſſe;</hi> and making a countenance to me, who ſtood cloſe by him, he roſe, and ſayd:
<hi>VVell, the houre is come; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, let vs goe, and that
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:2857:113"/>cheerefully</hi> And they all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing thus:
<q rend="margQuotes">Yea let it be done cheerefully,
<hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> cherefully, for the loue of <hi>Ieſus;</hi>
               </q> he turned towardes the <hi>Executioner,</hi> who kneeling down at his feete, to aske his pardon; <hi>Do your office</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>in the name of God, for ſo, he will haue it.</hi> Your Lordship (ſaid he) is to vnbutton your doublet, about your necke. And he (being as ready on the one ſide, as he was modeſt on the other) with his owne hands began to <pb n="236" facs="tcp:2857:114"/> vnbutton.
<q rend="margQuotes">It is not inough, ſaid the chiefe
<hi>Executioner;</hi> the doublet muſt be put off.</q> But the reſt of thoſe Officers of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> were not deſyrous, that he should put of his doublet. Yet the generous Noble Man ſaid, <hi>That howſoeuer, be would do it, if they thought it fit. For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>it shall not greatly trouble me; and if you haue a mind to it, I will strippe my ſelfe, from head to foot, for the loue of God.</hi> Already therefore, he was beginning to vntye himſelf; but it ſufficed that he was
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:2857:114"/>vnbuttoned to the shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Then, one of the
<hi>Confortatori</hi> putting him in mind, of <hi>Non erubeſcam &amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>Officer</hi> comming to tye his arms, in ſuch a fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that, when he should be arriued at the blocke, his body might not haue much leaue to mooue; <hi>In the name of God</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>bind both my armes, and my handes too, if your will be ſuch. For
<note n="(s)" place="margin">This man had true faith in Chriſt our Lord, &amp; his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, who in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof, was ſo willing to ſuffer, as you ſee.</note> my Lord Ieſus, was yet, much worſe bound for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being therfore thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated, they caſt a
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:2857:115"/>gowne about his backe; and he kneeled downe, before the
<hi>Altar;</hi> in act, as if he had craued a benediction, at the handes of our Lord. And, without the leaſt change of colour, beginning the
<hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere,</hi> of himſelfe; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come as far as the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward roome, he pauſed there, with an incredible decency, and grace. And he ſayd, to ſome of the by-ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>Might I not thanke my Lord, the Gouernour of the Caſtle, before I dye?</hi> And they, preſenting I knowe
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:2857:115"/>not what excuſe, of his not being riſen, he accepted thereof; and commanded a Gentleman, who ſerued the <hi>Gouernour,</hi> that he should thanke him in his name. And hauing demanded par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of many of the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, &amp; exhorting them in ſome very few wordes to vertue; by the example, which there they had before their eyes of the contrary, he went on with the very ſame verſe of the <hi>Miſerere,</hi> where he had left before. And ſometymes, turning <pb n="240" facs="tcp:2857:116"/>towardes me, he would be ſaying, <hi>Come
<note n="(t)" place="margin">See whether this Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron were afraid of death or no.</note> Father, come; to heauen, to heauen.</hi> And it was a ſtrang thing, that he being in pantofles, &amp; going downe ſuch a long paire of ſtaiers, as that is; (which ſtayers are much broken by reaſon of the Artillery, which vpon freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is drawne vp &amp; downe by that way) yet did not his foot once ſlipp. Nay, &amp; I, failing to tread right ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes, though I were in shoos, he willed me to take care of my ſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="241" facs="tcp:2857:116"/>
            <p>When he was arriued to the other open ſtayres, where many perſons of the <hi>Caſtle</hi> were to ſee him; one of the
<hi>Confortatori,</hi> who was well experienced in thoſe occaſions, and ſtood on the one hand, placing a <hi>Crucifixe</hi> before him (and as it were couering him therewith) cryed out, with a ſtronge voice, <hi>Let
<note n="(u)" place="margin">Viua Gieſu Chriſte.</note> Chriſt Ieſus liue;</hi> be not frighted, my Lord. To which he, (after he had ended the Verſe, which he was pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing) made this anſweare; <hi>Yea,
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:2857:117"/>let Chriſt Ieſus liue; in whome, whilſt I am hoping, I do not feare to be confounded.</hi> And then ſaid I, <hi>In te Domine ſperaui, non confundar in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num;</hi> which being repeated by him, he ſpake thus to them; <hi>Take
<note n="(x)" place="margin">A noble courage.</note> the</hi> Crucifixe <hi>aſide; let all the people ſee me. For if I be good for nothing els, at leaſt I may ſerue them, for an example.</hi> There paſſed one that way, with a bottle of wine in his hand, who ſaluted the
<hi>Baron,</hi> vpon his knee, and the <hi>Baron,</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly reſaluted him; and <pb n="243" facs="tcp:2857:117"/>ſo returned to the ſame verſe of the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> which he had formerly begunne. Soone after, paſſing through the people, which ſtoode there, a little, thicke, he ſayd; <hi>Learne
<note n="(y)" place="margin">Few wordes, and well choſen. It is not there the faſhion, for a man to ſtand prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, at the place of his executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> by my exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to liue well, and pray for me.</hi> And thus with <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iaculatory prayers,</hi> he came to the blocke, where there was ſtore of lookers on.</p>
            <p>The intrepide <hi>Baron</hi> pauſing there, ſayd thus. <hi>I would deſire, in theſe laſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of my life, to ſee, at leaſt, and ſalute, &amp; thanke, the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant <pb n="244" facs="tcp:2857:118"/>Gouernour of the Caſtle, ſince I cannot ſee my Lord, the Gouernour.</hi> But the
<hi>Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> by no means reſoluing to go towardes him (for the extreme tendernes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was taken) the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Youth, perceauing it, and turning to me, ſayd; <hi>Father, his hart ſerueth him not to come; and perhaps I make the people stay too longe.</hi> O moſt valiant, &amp; moſt vndaunted mind, which was troubled more with the ſleight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodity of others, then with the apprehenſion of <pb n="245" facs="tcp:2857:118"/>his owne imminent death. At laſt, he cheerefully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncing forward, the <hi>Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant,</hi> came before him; &amp; the <hi>Baron,</hi> caſting himſelfe vpon his knee, ſaid to me, <hi>In courteſy, Father, take off my hat.</hi> Which the good Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman obſeruing,
<note n="(z)" place="margin">A kind co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention who ſhould moſt exceed in cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy.</note> did, with a moſt bitter, &amp; lowd crye of teares, euen ſpread himſelf, all vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; and the by-ſtanders, vpon that occaſion, did caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues all, vpon their knees; nor was there any thing heard, but a loud voice of <pb n="246" facs="tcp:2857:119"/>teares This generous yong Lord, ſayd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thus to him. <hi>Syr, do not weepe; I had no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, but to ſalute you; to thank you; and to begge your pardon; as now I do, both of your ſelfe, and, in your perſon, at the hands of al them, who are preſent heer; deſiring them to learne at my coſt, and to pray for my ſoule.</hi> This he ſayd, with ſo ſtronge a voice, as that he was heard, notwithſtanding the noiſe of their weeping. I alſo, was not able to ſtay my teares; when he leaning towardes myne eare, ſpake theſe very
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:2857:119"/>wordes, now below, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had done, aboue:
<hi>Behould, your Reuerence is wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping; and yet ſtill you tell me, that I muſt haue a Noble Hart.</hi> Then hauing repeated, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers times, <hi>In manus tuas Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, commendo ſpiritum meum;</hi> and, <hi>Suſcipe me Domine, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum eloquium tuum, &amp; non confundas me ab expectatione mea;</hi> he was wished to aſcend and then to lay himſelfe downe vpon the Scaffold. At the ſame inſtant, one of the <hi>Confortatori</hi> ſaying to him, <hi>Cheerefully Signor Troi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, <pb n="248" facs="tcp:2857:120"/>couragiouſly Signor Troilo;</hi> and a whole crye of prayers being raiſed, and made by all the company for him; that valiant Hart, did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere euen with a ſmiling countenance; <hi>Know
<note n="(a)" place="margin">A no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and holy, valiant hart.</note> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, that I dye cheerefully, for the</hi> Loue <hi>of</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp; in</hi> Pennance <hi>for my ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As therefore he was laying down his head; <hi>where</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>is the Father?</hi> And turning towards the <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner,</hi> he ſayd, <hi>Stay a whyle; for I will be reconciled.</hi> And beckning me, firſt, towards <pb n="249" facs="tcp:2857:120"/>him with his countenance;
<hi>Father</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>on this hand, I place my</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Theſe Saines he vſed, as interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours for him to Chriſt our Lord.</note> Good Angell; <hi>and on that,</hi> S. Paul, <hi>and</hi> S. Iohn the Baptiſt; <hi>our</hi> B. Lady,
<hi>shall ſtand before. Your Reuerence muſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the promiſe, which you made me. I will ſay,</hi> O bone Ieſu, eſto mihi Ieſus; <hi>O good Lord Ieſus, be thou a Ieſus to me; and when you shall ſee, that the corde is in cutting, you muſt ſay,</hi> Ego te abſoluo &amp;c. <hi>that ſo, when I shall inuoke the name of Ieſus; and you</hi> abſolue me; <hi>my ſoule may begin her iourney, <pb n="250" facs="tcp:2857:121"/>from this body of myne, towards heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the mercy of my Lord, as I confide it shall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that I was ſo mightily amazed within my ſelfe, &amp; I fell into ſuch an exceſſe of weeping, that I had not a word to anſwere, at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, but in the language of teares. And he, in laying his head vpon the blocke, expreſly ſpake theſe very wordes: <hi>Deare Father, draw neere me. Let it ſuffice, and I take you to witnes, That
<note n="(c)" place="margin">So that his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and courage was far from fayling him; &amp; perhaps there is hardly to be found in any hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, a nobler Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, of wiſdom, preſence of mind, magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity.</note> I proteſt my ſeife, in my deſire to
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:2857:121"/>lay downe a thouſand heads, in this one head of myne; and in this one life, to offer vp a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand liues. I accuſe my ſelfe, for not doing it, with that feruour of deuotion; that vehemency of Contrition; and that prompti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of reſignation, which I haue beene told, and taught. But I know not how to do more. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my ſelfe, as truly, of all the ſinnes, which I haue confeſſed vnto your Reuerence, as if now I did repeate them to you, one, by one. In</hi> Pennance, <hi>if it pleaſe you, I will giue my head to Chriſt, as a punishment which <pb n="252" facs="tcp:2857:122"/>is moſt deſerued by me; and of you I deſire</hi> Abſolution.</p>
            <p>So did this Noble hart, which neither was, nor was to be conquered, or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, lay downe that head, vpon the blocke. And ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then, <hi>Bring
<note n="(d)" place="margin">See how this true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> courage, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinues euen to the end, and in the end.</note> hither the</hi> Crucifixe,
<hi>that I may ſee it;</hi> he began alſo to ſay, <hi>O bone Ieſu, ſis mihi Ieſus; O good Lord Ieſus, be a Ieſus to me,</hi> being accompanyed by all the people, who were alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ady vpon their knees, and who alſo, inuoked the name of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> And my ſelf, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:2857:122"/>cloſe, at the one ſide of his head, and looking ſtill, when the <hi>Executioner</hi> would go about to cut the corde, as ſoone as I ſaw, that the knife was lifted vp, for that purpoſe, I ſaid out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, <hi>Ego
<note n="(e)" place="margin">I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thy ſinnes in the name of the Father, &amp; of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt.</note> te abſoluo ab omnibus peccatis tuis, in nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Patris, &amp; Filij, &amp; Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Sancti, Amen.</hi> He did then, both more ſpeedily, and more lowdly then was his cuſtome, ſay, <hi>Ieſu, ſis mihi Ieſus; O Ieſus, be thou a Ieſus to me.</hi> And at the inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, his head flew off, at once,
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:2857:123"/>from his body. And my ſelfe, with many others alſo, did ſee, that his head being already cut off, did produce the laſt ſyllable of the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> with a ſtrong kind of hiſſe, or whiſper. And the ſoule, I truſt, did fly vp free, into
<note n="(f)" place="margin">His body was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred, in the
<hi>Chieſa Nuoua.</hi>
               </note> Heauen; ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all his former life, with a holy end; vpon that very day, of the yeare, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the moſt Illuſtrious Lord his Father, had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of this life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Sonne of his was
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:2857:123"/>borne; that former being the 18. of <hi>April, Anno Domini</hi> 1574.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
